<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DramaText>
  <PlayHeader>
    <Title>Macbeth</Title>
    <Author>William Shapespeare</Author>
    <Copyright>
      <Emp>Original gutenberg.org introduction:</Emp>
      <Br/> Project Gutenberg Etext of Macbeth by Shakespeare<Br/>PG has multiple editions of William Shakespeare's Complete Works <Br/>Copyright laws
      are changing all over the world, be sure to check the copyright laws for your country before posting these files!! <Br/>Please take a look at
      the important information in this header.<Br/>We encourage you to keep this file on your own disk, keeping an electronic path open for the next
      readers. Do not remove this. <Br/>Information on contacting Project Gutenberg to get Etexts, and further information is included below. We need
      your donations. <Br/>Project Gutenberg Etext of Macbeth by Shakespeare ******This file should be named 2ws3410.txt or 2ws3410.zip******
      <Br/>Corrected EDITIONS of our etexts get a new NUMBER, 2ws3411.txt<Br/>VERSIONS based on separate sources get new LETTER, 2ws3410a.txt
      <Br/>This etext was prepared by the PG Shakespeare Team, a team of about twenty Project Gutenberg volunteers. <Br/>Project Gutenberg Etexts are
      usually created from multiple editions, all of which are in the Public Domain in the United States, unless a copyright notice is included.
      Therefore, we usually do NOT! keep these books in compliance with any particular paper edition. <Br/>We are now trying to release all our books
      one month in advance of the official release dates, leaving time for better editing. <Br/>Please note: neither this list nor its contents are
      final till midnight of the last day of the month of any such announcement.<Br/>The official release date of all Project Gutenberg Etexts is
      at<Br/>Midnight, Central Time, of the last day of the stated month. A preliminary version may often be posted for suggestion, comment and
      editing by those who wish to do so. To be sure you have an up to date first edition [xxxxx10x.xxx] please check file sizes in the first week of
      the next month. Since our ftp program has a bug in it that scrambles the date [tried to fix and failed] a look at the file size will have to do,
      but we will try to see a new copy has at least one byte more or less. <Br/>We produce about two million dollars for each hour we work. The time
      it takes us, a rather conservative estimate, is fifty hours to get any etext selected, entered, proofread, edited, copyright searched and
      analyzed, the copyright letters written, etc. This projected audience is one hundred million readers. If our value per text is nominally
      estimated at one dollar then we produce $2 million dollars per hour this year as we release thirty-six text files per month, or 432 more Etexts
      in 1999 for a total of 2000+<Br/>If these reach just 10% of the computerized population, then the total should reach over 200 billion Etexts
      given away this year. <Br/>The Goal of Project Gutenberg is to Give Away One Trillion Etext<Br/>Files by December 31, 2001. [10,000 x
      100,000,000 = 1 Trillion]<Br/>This is ten thousand titles each to one hundred million readers, which is only ~5% of the present number of
      computer users. <Br/>At our revised rates of production, we will reach only one-third of that goal by the end of 2001, or about 3,333 Etexts
      unless we manage to get some real funding; currently our funding is mostly from Michael Hart's salary at Carnegie-Mellon University, and an
      assortment of sporadic gifts; this salary is only good for a few more years, so we are looking for something to replace it, as we don't want
      Project Gutenberg to be so dependent on one person. <Br/>All donations should be made to "Project Gutenberg/CMU": and are tax deductible to the
      extent allowable by law. (CMU = Carnegie-<Br/>Mellon University). <Br/>Project Gutenberg<Br/>P. O. Box 2782<Br/>Champaign, IL 61825 <Br/>When
      all other email fails. . .try our Executive Director:<Br/>Michael S. Hart &lt;hart@pobox.com&gt; hart@pobox.com forwards to hart@prairienet.org
      and archive.org if your mail bounces from archive.org, I will still see it, if it bounces from prairienet.org, better resend later on. . . .
      <Br/>To access Project Gutenberg etexts, use any Web browser to view http://promo.net/pg. This site lists Etexts by author and by title, and
      includes information about how to get involved with Project Gutenberg. You could also download our past Newsletters, or subscribe here. This is
      one of our major sites, please email hart@pobox.com, for a more complete list of our various sites. <Br/>To go directly to the etext
      collections, use FTP or any<Br/>Web browser to visit a Project Gutenberg mirror (mirror sites are available on 7 continents; mirrors are listed
      at http://promo.net/pg). <Br/>ftp sunsite.unc.edu login: anonymous password: your@login cd pub/docs/books/gutenberg cd etext90 through etext99
      dir [to see files] get or mget [to get files. . .set bin for zip files]<Br/>GET GUTINDEX.?? [to get a year's listing of books, e.g.,
      GUTINDEX.99]<Br/>GET GUTINDEX.ALL [to get a listing of ALL books] <Br/>***START**THE SMALL PRINT!**FOR PUBLIC DOMAIN ETEXTS**START***<Br/>Why is
      this "Small Print!" statement here? You know: lawyers.<Br/>They tell us you might sue us if there is something wrong with your copy of this
      etext, even if you got it for free from someone other than us, and even if what's wrong is not our fault. So, among other things, this "Small
      Print!" statement disclaims most of our liability to you. It also tells you how you can distribute copies of this etext if you want to.
      <Br/>*BEFORE!* YOU USE OR READ THIS ETEXT<Br/>By using or reading any part of this PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm etext, you indicate that you understand,
      agree to and accept this "Small Print!" statement. If you do not, you can receive a refund of the money (if any) you paid for this etext by
      sending a request within 30 days of receiving it to the person you got it from. If you received this etext on a physical medium (such as a
      disk), you must return it with your request. <Br/>ABOUT PROJECT GUTENBERG-TM ETEXTS<Br/>This PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm etext, like most PROJECT
      GUTENBERG- tm etexts, is a "public domain" work distributed by Professor<Br/>Michael S. Hart through the Project Gutenberg Association
      at<Br/>Carnegie-Mellon University (the "Project"). Among other things, this means that no one owns a United States copyright on or for this
      work, so the Project (and you!) can copy and distribute it in the United States without permission and without paying copyright royalties.
      Special rules, set forth below, apply if you wish to copy and distribute this etext under the Project's "PROJECT GUTENBERG" trademark. <Br/>To
      create these etexts, the Project expends considerable efforts to identify, transcribe and proofread public domain works. Despite these efforts,
      the Project's etexts and any medium they may be on may contain "Defects". Among other things, Defects may take the form of incomplete,
      inaccurate or corrupt data, transcription errors, a copyright or other intellectual property infringement, a defective or damaged disk or other
      etext medium, a computer virus, or computer codes that damage or cannot be read by your equipment. <Br/>LIMITED WARRANTY; DISCLAIMER OF
      DAMAGES<Br/>But for the "Right of Replacement or Refund" described below, [1] the Project (and any other party you may receive this etext from
      as a PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm etext) disclaims all liability to you for damages, costs and expenses, including legal fees, and [2] YOU HAVE NO
      REMEDIES FOR NEGLIGENCE OR<Br/>UNDER STRICT LIABILITY, OR FOR BREACH OF WARRANTY OR CONTRACT,<Br/>INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO INDIRECT,
      CONSEQUENTIAL, PUNITIVE<Br/>OR INCIDENTAL DAMAGES, EVEN IF YOU GIVE NOTICE OF THE<Br/>POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES. <Br/>If you discover a Defect
      in this etext within 90 days of receiving it, you can receive a refund of the money (if any) you paid for it by sending an explanatory note
      within that time to the person you received it from. If you received it on a physical medium, you must return it with your note, and such person
      may choose to alternatively give you a replacement copy. If you received it electronically, such person may choose to alternatively give you a
      second opportunity to receive it electronically. <Br/>THIS ETEXT IS OTHERWISE PROVIDED TO YOU "AS-IS". NO OTHER<Br/>WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND,
      EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, ARE MADE TO YOU AS<Br/>TO THE ETEXT OR ANY MEDIUM IT MAY BE ON, INCLUDING BUT NOT<Br/>LIMITED TO WARRANTIES OF
      MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A<Br/>PARTICULAR PURPOSE. <Br/>Some states do not allow disclaimers of implied warranties or the exclusion or
      limitation of consequential damages, so the above disclaimers and exclusions may not apply to you, and you may have other legal rights.
      <Br/>INDEMNITY<Br/>You will indemnify and hold the Project, its directors, officers, members and agents harmless from all liability, cost and
      expense, including legal fees, that arise directly or indirectly from any of the following that you do or cause: [1] distribution of this etext,
      [2] alteration, modification, or addition to the etext, or [3] any Defect. <Br/>DISTRIBUTION UNDER "PROJECT GUTENBERG-tm"<Br/>You may distribute
      copies of this etext electronically, or by disk, book or any other medium if you either delete this "Small Print!" and all other references to
      Project Gutenberg, or: <Br/>[1] Only give exact copies of it. Among other things, this requires that you do not remove, alter or modify the
      etext or this "small print!" statement. You may however, if you wish, distribute this etext in machine readable binary, compressed, mark-up, or
      proprietary form, including any form resulting from conversion by word pro- cessing or hypertext software, but only so long as *EITHER*:
      <Br/>[*] The etext, when displayed, is clearly readable, and does *not* contain characters other than those intended by the author of the work,
      although tilde (~), asterisk (*) and underline (_) characters may be used to convey punctuation intended by the author, and additional
      characters may be used to indicate hypertext links; OR <Br/>[*] The etext may be readily converted by the reader at no expense into plain ASCII,
      EBCDIC or equivalent form by the program that displays the etext (as is the case, for instance, with most word processors);<Br/>OR <Br/>[*] You
      provide, or agree to also provide on request at no additional cost, fee or expense, a copy of the etext in its original plain ASCII form (or in
      EBCDIC or other equivalent proprietary form). <Br/>[2] Honor the etext refund and replacement provisions of this "Small Print!" statement.
      <Br/>[3] Pay a trademark license fee to the Project of 20% of the net profits you derive calculated using the method you already use to
      calculate your applicable taxes. If you don't derive profits, no royalty is due. Royalties are payable to "Project Gutenberg
      Association/Carnegie-Mellon<Br/>University" within the 60 days following each date you prepare (or were legally required to prepare) your annual
      (or equivalent periodic) tax return. <Br/>WHAT IF YOU *WANT* TO SEND MONEY EVEN IF YOU DON'T HAVE TO?<Br/>The Project gratefully accepts
      contributions in money, time, scanning machines, OCR software, public domain etexts, royalty free copyright licenses, and every other sort of
      contribution you can think of. Money should be paid to "Project Gutenberg<Br/>Association / Carnegie-Mellon University". <Br/>This etext was
      prepared by the PG Shakespeare Team, a team of about twenty Project Gutenberg volunteers. </Copyright>
  </PlayHeader>
  <Roles>
    <!-- Main characters: -->
    <Role role-id="DUNCAN">
      <Name>Duncan</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>King of Scotland</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="MALCOLM">
      <Name>Malcolm</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Son of Duncan</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="DONALBAIN">
      <Name>Donalbain</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Son of Duncan</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="MACBETH">
      <Name>Macbeth</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>General in the King's army</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="BANQUO">
      <Name>Banquo</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>General in the King's army</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="MACDUFF">
      <Name>Macduff</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Nobleman of Scotland</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="LENNOX">
      <Name>Lennox</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Nobleman of Scotland</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="ROSS">
      <Name>Ross</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Nobleman of Scotland</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="MENTEITH">
      <Name>Menteith</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Nobleman of Scotland</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="ANGUS">
      <Name>Angus</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Nobleman of Scotland</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="CAITHNESS">
      <Name>Caithness</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Nobleman of Scotland</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="FLEANCE">
      <Name>Fleance</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Son to Banquo</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="SIWARD">
      <Name>Siward</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Earl of Northumberland, General of the English Forces</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="YOUNGSIWARD">
      <Name>Young Siward</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Son of Siward</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="SEYTON">
      <Name>Seyton</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>an Officer attending on Macbeth</Description>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="SONOFMACDUFF">
      <Name>Son Macduff</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
      <Description>Son to Macduff</Description>
    </Role>
    <!-- Females -->
    <Role role-id="LADYMACBETH">
      <Name>Lady Macbeth</Name>
      <PreferredSex>female</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="LADYMACDUFF">
      <Name>Lady Macduff</Name>
      <PreferredSex>female</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <!-- Others -->
    <Role role-id="ATTENDANT">
      <Name>Attendant</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="ATTENDANTS">
      <Name>Attendant</Name>
      <PreferredSex>group</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="PORTER">
      <Name>Porter</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="OLDMAN">
      <Name>Old man</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="FIRSTMURDERER">
      <Name>First murderer</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="SECONDMURDERER">
      <Name>Second murderer</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="THIRDMURDERER">
      <Name>Third murderer</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="SERVANT">
      <Name>Servant</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="APPARITION">
      <Name>Apparition</Name>
      <PreferredSex>na</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="MESSENGER">
      <Name>Messenger</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="DOCTOR">
      <Name>Doctor</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="GENTLEWOMAN">
      <Name>Gentlewoman</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="FIRSTWITCH">
      <Name>First witch</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="SECONDWITCH">
      <Name>Second witch</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="THIRDWITCH">
      <Name>Third witch</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="HECATE">
      <Name>Hecate</Name>
      <PreferredSex>female</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="SOLDIER">
      <Name>Soldier</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="LADIES">
      <Name>Ladies</Name>
      <PreferredSex>group</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="LORD">
      <Name>Lord</Name>
      <PreferredSex>male</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="LORDS">
      <Name>Lords</Name>
      <PreferredSex>group</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <Role role-id="SOLDIERS">
      <Name>Soldiers</Name>
      <PreferredSex>group</PreferredSex>
    </Role>
    <!-- Role groups: -->
    <RoleGroup role-id="THREEWITCHES" role-ref="FIRSTWITCH SECONDWITCH THIRDWITCH">
      <Name>Three witches</Name>
    </RoleGroup>
    <RoleGroup role-id="MURDERERS" role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER SECONDMURDERER THIRDMURDERER">
      <Name>Murderers</Name>
    </RoleGroup>
  </Roles>
  <Play>
    <Acts>
      <Act>
        <Scenes>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>An open Place. Thunder and Lightning.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="THREEWITCHES"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>When shall we three meet again?<Br/>In thunder, lightning, or in rain?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>When the hurlyburly's done,<Br/>When the battle's lost and won.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>That will be ere the set of sun.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Where the place?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Upon the heath.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>There to meet with Macbeth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>I come, Graymalkin!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="#all">
                <Text>Paddock calls:--anon:--<Br/>Fair is foul, and foul is fair:<Br/>Hover through the fog and filthy air.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="THREEWITCHES">Vanish</Exit>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>A Camp near Forres. Alarum within.</LocationDescription>
              <StartPresences>
                <StartPresence role-ref="SOLDIER">Wounded and bleeding</StartPresence>
              </StartPresences>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="DUNCAN MALCOLM DONALBAIN LENNOX ATTENDANTS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>What bloody man is that? He can report,<Br/>As seemeth by his plight, of the revolt<Br/>The newest state.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>This is the sergeant<Br/>Who, like a good and hardy soldier, fought 'Gainst my captivity.--Hail, brave friend!<Br/>Say to the
                  king the knowledge of the broil<Br/>As thou didst leave it.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SOLDIER">
                <Text>Doubtful it stood;<Br/>As two spent swimmers that do cling together<Br/>And choke their art. The merciless
                  Macdonwald,--<Br/>Worthy to be a rebel,--for to that<Br/>The multiplying villainies of nature<Br/>Do swarm upon him,--from the
                  Western isles<Br/>Of kerns and gallowglasses is supplied;<Br/>And fortune, on his damned quarrel smiling,<Br/>Show'd like a rebel's
                  whore. But all's too weak;<Br/>For brave Macbeth,--well he deserves that name,--<Br/>Disdaining fortune, with his brandish'd
                  steel,<Br/>Which smok'd with bloody execution,<Br/>Like valor's minion,<Br/>Carv'd out his passag tTill he fac'd the slave;<Br/>And
                  ne'er shook hands, nor bade farewell to him,<Br/>Till he unseam'd him from the nave to the chaps,<Br/>And fix'd his head upon our
                  battlements.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>O valiant cousin! worthy gentleman!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SOLDIER">
                <Text>As whence the sun 'gins his reflection<Br/>Shipwrecking storms and direful thunders break;<Br/>So from that spring, whence
                  comfort seem'd to come<Br/>Discomfort swells. Mark, King of Scotland, mark:<Br/>No sooner justice had, with valor
                  arm'd,<Br/>Compell'd these skipping kerns to trust their heels,<Br/>But the Norweyan lord, surveying vantage,<Br/>With furbish'd
                  arms and new supplies of men,<Br/>Began a fresh assault.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>Dismay'd not this<Br/>Our captains, Macbeth and Banquo?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SOLDIER">
                <Text>Yes;<Br/>As sparrows eagles, or the hare the lion.<Br/>If I say sooth, I must report they were<Br/>As cannons overcharg'd with
                  double cracks;<Br/>So they<Br/>Doubly redoubled strokes upon the foe:<Br/>Except they meant to bathe in reeking wounds,<Br/>Or
                  memorize another Golgotha,<Br/>I cannot tell:--<Br/>But I am faint; my gashes cry for help.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>So well thy words become thee as thy wounds;<Br/>They smack of honor both.--Go, get him surgeons.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="SOLDIER ATTENDANTS"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>The worthy Thane of Ross.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>What a haste looks through his eyes! So should he look<Br/>That seems to speak things strange.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="ROSS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>God save the King!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>Whence cam'st thou, worthy thane?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>From Fife, great king;<Br/>Where the Norweyan banners flout the sky<Br/>And fan our people cold.<Br/>Norway himself, with
                  terrible numbers,<Br/>Assisted by that most disloyal traitor<Br/>The Thane of Cawdor, began a dismal conflict;<Br/>Till that
                  Bellona's bridegroom, lapp'd in proof,<Br/>Confronted him with self-comparisons,<Br/>Point against point rebellious, arm 'gainst
                  arm,<Br/>Curbing his lavish spirit: and, to conclude,<Br/>The victory fell on us.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>Great happiness!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>That now<Br/>Sweno, the Norways' king, craves composition;<Br/>Nor would we deign him burial of his men<Br/>Till he disbursed,
                  at Saint Colme's-inch,<Br/>Ten thousand dollars to our general use.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>No more that Thane of Cawdor shall deceive<Br/>Our bosom interest:--go pronounce his present death,<Br/>And with his former
                  title greet Macbeth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>I'll see it done.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>What he hath lost, noble Macbeth hath won.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>A heath. Thunder.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="THREEWITCHES"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Where hast thou been, sister?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Killing swine.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>Sister, where thou?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>A sailor's wife had chestnuts in her lap,<Br/>And mounch'd, and mounch'd, and mounch'd:--"Give me," quoth I: "Aroint thee,
                  witch!" the rump-fed ronyon cries.<Br/>Her husband's to Aleppo gone, master o' the Tiger:<Br/>But in a sieve I'll thither
                  sail,<Br/>And, like a rat without a tail,<Br/>I'll do, I'll do, and I'll do.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>I'll give thee a wind.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Thou art kind.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>And I another.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>I myself have all the other:<Br/>And the very ports they blow,<Br/>All the quarters that they know<Br/>I' the shipman's
                  card.<Br/>I will drain him dry as hay:<Br/>Sleep shall neither night nor day<Br/>Hang upon his pent-house lid;<Br/>He shall live a
                  man forbid:<Br/>Weary seven-nights nine times nine<Br/>Shall he dwindle, peak, and pine:<Br/>Though his bark cannot be lost,<Br/>Yet
                  it shall be tempest-tost.--<Br/>Look what I have.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Show me, show me.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Here I have a pilot's thumb,<Br/>Wreck'd as homeward he did come.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Drum within.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>A drum, a drum!<Br/>Macbeth doth come.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="#all">
                <Text>The weird sisters, hand in hand,<Br/>Posters of the sea and land,<Br/>Thus do go about, about:<Br/>Thrice to thine, and thrice
                  to mine,<Br/>And thrice again, to make up nine:--<Br/>Peace!--the charm's wound up.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH BANQUO"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>So foul and fair a day I have not seen.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>How far is't call'd to Forres?--What are these<Br/>So wither'd, and so wild in their attire,<Br/>That look not like the
                  inhabitants o' the earth,<Br/>And yet are on't?--Live you? or are you aught<Br/>That man may question? You seem to understand
                  me,<Br/>By each at once her chappy finger laying<Br/>Upon her skinny lips:--you should be women,<Br/>And yet your beards forbid me
                  to interpret<Br/>That you are so.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Speak, if you can;--what are you?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>All hail, Macbeth! hail to thee, Thane of Glamis!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>All hail, Macbeth! hail to thee, Thane of Cawdor!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>All hail, Macbeth! that shalt be king hereafter!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Good sir, why do you start; and seem to fear<Br/>Things that do sound so fair?-- I' the name of truth,<Br/>Are ye fantastical,
                  or that indeed<Br/>Which outwardly ye show? My noble partner<Br/>You greet with present grace and great prediction<Br/>Of noble
                  having and of royal hope,<Br/>That he seems rapt withal:--to me you speak not:<Br/>If you can look into the seeds of time,<Br/>And
                  say which grain will grow, and which will not,<Br/>Speak then to me, who neither beg nor fear<Br/>Your favors nor your hate.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Hail!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Hail!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>Hail!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Lesser than Macbeth, and greater.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Not so happy, yet much happier.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>Thou shalt get kings, though thou be none:<Br/>So all hail, Macbeth and Banquo!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Banquo and Macbeth, all hail!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Stay, you imperfect speakers, tell me more:<Br/>By Sinel's death I know I am Thane of Glamis;<Br/>But how of Cawdor? The Thane
                  of Cawdor lives,<Br/>A prosperous gentleman; and to be king<Br/>Stands not within the prospect of belief,<Br/>No more than to be
                  Cawdor. Say from whence<Br/>You owe this strange intelligence? or why<Br/>Upon this blasted heath you stop our way<Br/>With such
                  prophetic greeting?--Speak, I charge you.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="THREEWITCHES">Vanish</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>The earth hath bubbles, as the water has,<Br/>And these are of them:--whither are they vanish'd?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Into the air; and what seem'd corporal melted<Br/>As breath into the wind.--Would they had stay'd!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Were such things here as we do speak about?<Br/>Or have we eaten on the insane root<Br/>That takes the reason prisoner?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Your children shall be kings.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>You shall be king.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>And Thane of Cawdor too; went it not so?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>To the selfsame tune and words. Who's here?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="ROSS ANGUS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>The king hath happily receiv'd, Macbeth,<Br/>The news of thy success: and when he reads<Br/>Thy personal venture in the rebels'
                  fight,<Br/>His wonders and his praises do contend<Br/>Which should be thine or his: silenc'd with that,<Br/>In viewing o'er the rest
                  o' the self-same day,<Br/>He finds thee in the stout Norweyan ranks,<Br/>Nothing afeard of what thyself didst make,<Br/>Strange
                  images of death. As thick as hail<Br/>Came post with post; and every one did bear<Br/>Thy praises in his kingdom's great
                  defense,<Br/>And pour'd them down before him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ANGUS">
                <Text>We are sent<Br/>To give thee, from our royal master, thanks;<Br/>Only to herald thee into his sight,<Br/>Not pay thee.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>And, for an earnest of a greater honor,<Br/>He bade me, from him, call thee Thane of Cawdor:<Br/>In which addition, hail, most
                  worthy thane,<Br/>For it is thine.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>What, can the devil speak true?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>The Thane of Cawdor lives: why do you dress me<Br/>In borrow'd robes?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ANGUS">
                <Text>Who was the Thane lives yet;<Br/>But under heavy judgement bears that life<Br/>Which he deserves to lose. Whether he was
                  combin'd<Br/>With those of Norway, or did line the rebel<Br/>With hidden help and vantage, or that with both<Br/>He labour'd in his
                  country's wreck, I know not;<Br/>But treasons capital, confess'd and proved,<Br/>Have overthrown him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>
                  <Instruction>Aside</Instruction> Glamis, and Thane of Cawdor:<Br/>The greatest is behind.--Thanks for your pains.--<Br/>Do you not
                  hope your children shall be kings,<Br/>When those that gave the Thane of Cawdor to me<Br/>Promis'd no less to them? </Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>That, trusted home,<Br/>Might yet enkindle you unto the crown,<Br/>Besides the Thane of Cawdor. But 'tis strange:<Br/>And
                  oftentimes to win us to our harm,<Br/>The instruments of darkness tell us truths;<Br/>Win us with honest trifles, to betray's<Br/>In
                  deepest consequence.--<Br/>Cousins, a word, I pray you.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>
                  <Instruction>Aside</Instruction> Two truths are told,<Br/>As happy prologues to the swelling act<Br/>Of the imperial theme.--I thank
                  you, gentlemen.-- <Instruction>Aside</Instruction> This supernatural soliciting<Br/>Cannot be ill; cannot be good:--if ill,<Br/>Why
                  hath it given me earnest of success,<Br/>Commencing in a truth? I am Thane of Cawdor:<Br/>If good, why do I yield to that
                  suggestion<Br/>Whose horrid image doth unfix my hair,<Br/>And make my seated heart knock at my ribs,<Br/>Against the use of nature?
                  Present fears<Br/>Are less than horrible imaginings:<Br/>My thought, whose murder yet is but fantastical,<Br/>Shakes so my single
                  state of man, that function<Br/>Is smother'd in surmise; and nothing is<Br/>But what is not. </Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Look, how our partner's rapt.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>
                  <Instruction>Aside</Instruction> If chance will have me king, why, chance may crown me<Br/>Without my stir. </Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>New honors come upon him,<Br/>Like our strange garments, cleave not to their mould<Br/>But with the aid of use.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>
                  <Instruction>Aside</Instruction> Come what come may,<Br/>Time and the hour runs through the roughest day. </Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Worthy Macbeth, we stay upon your leisure.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Give me your favor:--my dull brain was wrought<Br/>With things forgotten. Kind gentlemen, your pains<Br/>Are register'd where
                  every day I turn<Br/>The leaf to read them.--Let us toward the king.--<Br/>Think upon what hath chanc'd; and, at more time,<Br/>The
                  interim having weigh'd it, let us speak<Br/>Our free hearts each to other.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Very gladly.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Till then, enough.--Come, friends.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Forres. A Room in the Palace.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="DUNCAN MALCOLM DONALBAIN LENNOX ATTENDANTS">Flourish.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>Is execution done on Cawdor? Are not<Br/>Those in commission yet return'd?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>My liege,<Br/>They are not yet come back. But I have spoke<Br/>With one that saw him die: who did report,<Br/>That very frankly
                  he confess'd his treasons;<Br/>Implor'd your highness' pardon; and set forth<Br/>A deep repentance: nothing in his life<Br/>Became
                  him like the leaving it; he died<Br/>As one that had been studied in his death,<Br/>To throw away the dearest thing he ow'd<Br/>As
                  'twere a careless trifle.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>There's no art<Br/>To find the mind's construction in the face:<Br/>He was a gentleman on whom I built<Br/>An absolute
                  trust.--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH BANQUO ROSS ANGUS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>O worthiest cousin!<Br/>The sin of my ingratitude even now<Br/>Was heavy on me: thou art so far before,<Br/>That swiftest wing
                  of recompense is slow<Br/>To overtake thee. Would thou hadst less deserv'd;<Br/>That the proportion both of thanks and
                  payment<Br/>Might have been mine! only I have left to say,<Br/>More is thy due than more than all can pay.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>The service and the loyalty I owe,<Br/>In doing it, pays itself. Your highness' part<Br/>Is to receive our duties: and our
                  duties<Br/>Are to your throne and state, children and servants;<Br/>Which do but what they should, by doing everything<Br/>Safe
                  toward your love and honor.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>Welcome hither:<Br/>I have begun to plant thee, and will labor<Br/>To make thee full of growing.--Noble Banquo,<Br/>That hast no
                  less deserv'd, nor must be known<Br/>No less to have done so,let me infold thee<Br/>And hold thee to my heart.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>There if I grow,<Br/>The harvest is your own.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>My plenteous joys,<Br/>Wanton in fulness, seek to hide themselves<Br/>In drops of sorrow.--Sons, kinsmen, thanes,<Br/>And you
                  whose places are the nearest, know,<Br/>We will establish our estate upon<Br/>Our eldest, Malcolm; whom we name hereafter<Br/>The
                  Prince of Cumberland: which honor must<Br/>Not unaccompanied invest him only,<Br/>But signs of nobleness, like stars, shall
                  shine<Br/>On all deservers.--From hence to Inverness,<Br/>And bind us further to you.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>The rest is labor, which is not us'd for you:<Br/>I'll be myself the harbinger, and make joyful<Br/>The hearing of my wife with
                  your approach;<Br/>So, humbly take my leave.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>My worthy Cawdor!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>
                  <Instruction>Aside</Instruction> The Prince of Cumberland!--That is a step,<Br/>On which I must fall down, or else o'erleap,<Br/>For
                  in my way it lies. Stars, hide your fires!<Br/>Let not light see my black and deep desires:<Br/>The eye wink at the hand! yet let
                  that be,<Br/>Which the eye fears, when it is done, to see. </Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>True, worthy Banquo!--he is full so valiant;<Br/>And in his commendations I am fed,--<Br/>It is a banquet to me. Let us after
                  him,<Br/>Whose care is gone before to bid us welcome:<Br/>It is a peerless kinsman.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all">Flourish</Exit>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Inverness. A Room in Macbeth's Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH">Reading a letter.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>"They met me in the day of success; and I have learned by the perfectest report they have more in them than mortal knowledge.
                  When I burned in desire to question them further, they made themselves air, into which they vanished.<Br/>Whiles I stood rapt in the
                  wonder of it, came missives from the king, who all-hailed me, 'Thane of Cawdor'; by which title, before, these weird sisters saluted
                  me, and referred me to the coming on of time, with 'Hail, king that shalt be!' This have<Br/>I thought good to deliver thee, my
                  dearest partner of greatness; that thou mightst not lose the dues of rejoicing, by being ignorant of what greatness is promised
                  thee. Lay it to thy heart, and farewell."<Br/><Br/> Glamis thou art, and Cawdor; and shalt be<Br/>What thou art promis'd; yet do I
                  fear thy nature;<Br/>It is too full o' the milk of human kindness<Br/>To catch the nearest way: thou wouldst be great;<Br/>Art not
                  without ambition; but without<Br/>The illness should attend it. What thou wouldst highly,<Br/>That wouldst thou holily; wouldst not
                  play false,<Br/>And yet wouldst wrongly win: thou'dst have, great Glamis,<Br/>That which cries, "Thus thou must do, if thou have
                  it:<Br/>And that which rather thou dost fear to do<Br/>Than wishest should be undone." Hie thee hither,<Br/>That I may pour my
                  spirits in thine ear;<Br/>And chastise with the valor of my tongue<Br/>All that impedes thee from the golden round,<Br/>Which fate
                  and metaphysical aid doth seem<Br/>To have thee crown'd withal.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="ATTENDANT"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="ATTENDANT">
                <Text>The king comes here tonight.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Thou'rt mad to say it:<Br/>Is not thy master with him? who, were't so,<Br/>Would have inform'd for preparation.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ATTENDANT">
                <Text>So please you, it is true:--our thane is coming:<Br/>One of my fellows had the speed of him;<Br/>Who, almost dead for breath,
                  had scarcely more<Br/>Than would make up his message.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Give him tending;<Br/>He brings great news.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="ATTENDANT"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>The raven himself is hoarse<Br/>That croaks the fatal entrance of Duncan<Br/>Under my battlements. Come, you spirits<Br/>That
                  tend on mortal thoughts, unsex me here;<Br/>And fill me, from the crown to the toe, top-full<Br/>Of direst cruelty! make thick my
                  blood,<Br/>Stop up the access and passage to remorse,<Br/>That no compunctious visitings of nature<Br/>Shake my fell purpose, nor
                  keep peace between<Br/>The effect and it! Come to my woman's breasts,<Br/>And take my milk for gall, your murdering
                  ministers,<Br/>Wherever in your sightless substances<Br/>You wait on nature's mischief! Come, thick night,<Br/>And pall thee in the
                  dunnest smoke of hell<Br/>That my keen knife see not the wound it makes<Br/>Nor heaven peep through the blanket of the dark<Br/>To
                  cry, "Hold, hold!"</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Great Glamis! Worthy Cawdor!<Br/>Greater than both, by the all-hail hereafter!<Br/>Thy letters have transported me
                  beyond<Br/>This ignorant present, and I feel now<Br/>The future in the instant.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>My dearest love,<Br/>Duncan comes here tonight.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>And when goes hence?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>To-morrow,--as he purposes.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>O, never<Br/>Shall sun that morrow see!<Br/>Your face, my thane, is as a book where men<Br/>May read strange matters:--to
                  beguile the time,<Br/>Look like the time; bear welcome in your eye,<Br/>Your hand, your tongue: look like the innocent
                  flower,<Br/>But be the serpent under't. He that's coming<Br/>Must be provided for: and you shall put<Br/>This night's great business
                  into my despatch;<Br/>Which shall to all our nights and days to come<Br/>Give solely sovereign sway and masterdom.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>We will speak further.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Only look up clear;<Br/>To alter favor ever is to fear:<Br/>Leave all the rest to me.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. Before the Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Instruction>Hautboys. Servants of Macbeth attending.</Instruction>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="DUNCAN MALCOLM DONALBAIN BANQUO LENNOX MACDUFF ROSS ANGUS ATTENDANTS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>This castle hath a pleasant seat: the air<Br/>Nimbly and sweetly recommends itself<Br/>Unto our gentle senses.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>This guest of summer,<Br/>The temple-haunting martlet, does approve<Br/>By his lov'd mansionry, that the heaven's
                  breath<Br/>Smells wooingly here: no jutty, frieze, buttress,<Br/>Nor coigne of vantage, but this bird hath made<Br/>His pendant bed
                  and procreant cradle:<Br/>Where they most breed and haunt, I have observ'd<Br/>The air is delicate.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>See, see, our honour'd hostess!--<Br/>The love that follows us sometime is our trouble,<Br/>Which still we thank as love. Herein
                  I teach you<Br/>How you shall bid God ild us for your pains,<Br/>And thank us for your trouble.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>All our service<Br/>In every point twice done, and then done double,<Br/>Were poor and single business to contend<Br/>Against
                  those honours deep and broad wherewith<Br/>Your majesty loads our house: for those of old,<Br/>And the late dignities heap'd up to
                  them,<Br/>We rest your hermits.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>Where's the Thane of Cawdor?<Br/>We cours'd him at the heels, and had a purpose<Br/>To be his purveyor: but he rides
                  well;<Br/>And his great love, sharp as his spur, hath holp him<Br/>To his home before us. Fair and noble hostess,<Br/>We are your
                  guest tonight.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Your servants ever<Br/>Have theirs, themselves, and what is theirs, in compt,<Br/>To make their audit at your highness'
                  pleasure,<Br/>Still to return your own.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DUNCAN">
                <Text>Give me your hand;<Br/>Conduct me to mine host: we love him highly,<Br/>And shall continue our graces towards him.<Br/>By your
                  leave, hostess.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. A Lobby in the Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Instruction>Hautboys and torches. Enter, and pass over, a Sewer and divers<Br/>Servants with dishes and service.</Instruction>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>If it were done when 'tis done, then 'twere well<Br/>It were done quickly. If the assassination<Br/>Could trammel up the
                  consequence, and catch,<Br/>With his surcease, success; that but this blow<Br/>Might be the be-all and the end-all--here,<Br/>But
                  here, upon this bank and shoal of time,--<Br/>We'd jump the life to come. But in these cases<Br/>We still have judgement here; that
                  we but teach<Br/>Bloody instructions, which being taught, return<Br/>To plague the inventor: this even-handed justice<Br/>Commends
                  the ingredients of our poison'd chalice<Br/>To our own lips. He's here in double trust:<Br/>First, as I am his kinsman and his
                  subject,<Br/>Strong both against the deed: then, as his host,<Br/>Who should against his murderer shut the door,<Br/>Not bear the
                  knife myself. Besides, this Duncan<Br/>Hath borne his faculties so meek, hath been<Br/>So clear in his great office, that his
                  virtues<Br/>Will plead like angels, trumpet-tongued, against<Br/>The deep damnation of his taking-off:<Br/>And pity, like a naked
                  new-born babe,<Br/>Striding the blast, or heaven's cherubin, hors'd<Br/>Upon the sightless couriers of the air,<Br/>Shall blow the
                  horrid deed in every eye,<Br/>That tears shall drown the wind.--I have no spur<Br/>To prick the sides of my intent, but
                  only<Br/>Vaulting ambition, which o'erleaps itself,<Br/>And falls on the other.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>He has almost supp'd: why have you left the chamber?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Hath he ask'd for me?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Know you not he has?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>We will proceed no further in this business:<Br/>He hath honour'd me of late; and I have bought<Br/>Golden opinions from all
                  sorts of people,<Br/>Which would be worn now in their newest gloss,<Br/>Not cast aside so soon.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Was the hope drunk<Br/>Wherein you dress'd yourself? hath it slept since?<Br/>And wakes it now, to look so green and pale<Br/>At
                  what it did so freely? From this time<Br/>Such I account thy love. Art thou afeard<Br/>To be the same in thine own act and
                  valor<Br/>As thou art in desire? Wouldst thou have that<Br/>Which thou esteem'st the ornament of life,<Br/>And live a coward in
                  thine own esteem;<Br/>Letting "I dare not" wait upon "I would,"<Br/>Like the poor cat i' the adage?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Pr'ythee, peace!<Br/>I dare do all that may become a man;<Br/>Who dares do more is none.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>What beast was't, then,<Br/>That made you break this enterprise to me?<Br/>When you durst do it, then you were a man;<Br/>And,
                  to be more than what you were, you would<Br/>Be so much more the man. Nor time nor place<Br/>Did then adhere, and yet you would make
                  both:<Br/>They have made themselves, and that their fitness now<Br/>Does unmake you. I have given suck, and know<Br/>How tender 'tis
                  to love the babe that milks me:<Br/>I would, while it was smiling in my face,<Br/>Have pluck'd my nipple from his boneless
                  gums<Br/>And dash'd the brains out, had I so sworn as you<Br/>Have done to this.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>If we should fail?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>We fail!<Br/>But screw your courage to the sticking-place,<Br/>And we'll not fail. When Duncan is asleep,--<Br/>Whereto the
                  rather shall his day's hard journey<Br/>Soundly invite him, his two chamberlains<Br/>Will I with wine and wassail so
                  convince<Br/>That memory, the warder of the brain,<Br/>Shall be a fume, and the receipt of reason<Br/>A limbec only: when in swinish
                  sleep<Br/>Their drenched natures lie as in a death,<Br/>What cannot you and I perform upon<Br/>The unguarded Duncan? what not put
                  upon<Br/>His spongy officers; who shall bear the guilt<Br/>Of our great quell?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Bring forth men-children only;<Br/>For thy undaunted mettle should compose<Br/>Nothing but males. Will it not be
                  receiv'd,<Br/>When we have mark'd with blood those sleepy two<Br/>Of his own chamber, and us'd their very daggers,<Br/>That they
                  have don't?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Who dares receive it other,<Br/>As we shall make our griefs and clamor roar<Br/>Upon his death?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I am settled, and bend up<Br/>Each corporal agent to this terrible feat.<Br/>Away, and mock the time with fairest
                  show:<Br/>False face must hide what the false heart doth know.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
        </Scenes>
      </Act>
      <Act>
        <Scenes>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Inverness. Court within the Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="FLEANCE">Holds a torch</Entry>
                <Entry role-ref="BANQUO"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>How goes the night, boy?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FLEANCE">
                <Text>The moon is down; I have not heard the clock.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>And she goes down at twelve.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FLEANCE">
                <Text>I take't, 'tis later, sir.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Hold, take my sword.--There's husbandry in heaven;<Br/>Their candles are all out:--take thee that too.--<Br/>A heavy summons
                  lies like lead upon me,<Br/>And yet I would not sleep:--merciful powers,<Br/>Restrain in me the cursed thoughts that
                  nature<Br/>Gives way to in repose!--Give me my sword.<Br/>Who's there?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
                <Entry role-ref="SERVANT">Holding a torch</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>A friend.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>What, sir, not yet at rest? The king's a-bed:<Br/>He hath been in unusual pleasure and<Br/>Sent forth great largess to your
                  officers:<Br/>This diamond he greets your wife withal,<Br/>By the name of most kind hostess; and shut up<Br/>In measureless
                  content.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Being unprepar'd,<Br/>Our will became the servant to defect;<Br/>Which else should free have wrought.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>All's well.<Br/>I dreamt last night of the three weird sisters:<Br/>To you they have show'd some truth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I think not of them:<Br/>Yet, when we can entreat an hour to serve,<Br/>We would spend it in some words upon that
                  business,<Br/>If you would grant the time.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>At your kind'st leisure.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>If you shall cleave to my consent,--when 'tis,<Br/>It shall make honor for you.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>So I lose none<Br/>In seeking to augment it, but still keep<Br/>My bosom franchis'd, and allegiance clear,<Br/>I shall be
                  counsell'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Good repose the while!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Thanks, sir: the like to you!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="BANQUO FLEANCE"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Go bid thy mistress, when my drink is ready,<Br/>She strike upon the bell. Get thee to bed.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="SERVANT"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Is this a dagger which I see before me,<Br/>The handle toward my hand? Come, let me clutch thee:--<Br/>I have thee not, and yet
                  I see thee still.<Br/>Art thou not, fatal vision, sensible<Br/>To feeling as to sight? or art thou but<Br/>A dagger of the mind, a
                  false creation,<Br/>Proceeding from the heat-oppressed brain?<Br/>I see thee yet, in form as palpable<Br/>As this which now I
                  draw.<Br/>Thou marshall'st me the way that I was going;<Br/>And such an instrument I was to use.<Br/>Mine eyes are made the fools o'
                  the other senses,<Br/>Or else worth all the rest: I see thee still;<Br/>And on thy blade and dudgeon gouts of blood,<Br/>Which was
                  not so before.--There's no such thing:<Br/>It is the bloody business which informs<Br/>Thus to mine eyes.--Now o'er the one
                  half-world<Br/>Nature seems dead, and wicked dreams abuse<Br/>The curtain'd sleep; now witchcraft celebrates<Br/>Pale Hecate's
                  offerings; and wither'd murder,<Br/>Alarum'd by his sentinel, the wolf,<Br/>Whose howl's his watch, thus with his stealthy
                  pace,<Br/>With Tarquin's ravishing strides, towards his design<Br/>Moves like a ghost.--Thou sure and firm-set earth,<Br/>Hear not
                  my steps, which way they walk, for fear<Br/>Thy very stones prate of my whereabout,<Br/>And take the present horror from the
                  time,<Br/>Which now suits with it.--Whiles I threat, he lives;<Br/>Words to the heat of deeds too cold breath gives.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>A bell rings.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I go, and it is done; the bell invites me.<Br/>Hear it not, Duncan, for it is a knell<Br/>That summons thee to heaven or to
                  hell.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Exits>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>That which hath made them drunk hath made me bold:<Br/>What hath quench'd them hath given me fire.--Hark!--Peace!<Br/>It was the
                  owl that shriek'd, the fatal bellman,<Br/>Which gives the stern'st good night. He is about it:<Br/>The doors are open; and the
                  surfeited grooms<Br/>Do mock their charge with snores: I have drugg'd their possets<Br/>That death and nature do contend about
                  them,<Br/>Whether they live or die.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH" offstage="1">
                <Text>Who's there?--what, ho!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Alack! I am afraid they have awak'd,<Br/>And 'tis not done: the attempt, and not the deed,<Br/>Confounds us.--Hark!--I laid
                  their daggers ready;<Br/>He could not miss 'em.--Had he not resembled<Br/>My father as he slept, I had done't.--My husband!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I have done the deed.--Didst thou not hear a noise?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>I heard the owl scream and the crickets cry.<Br/>Did not you speak?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>When?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Now.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>As I descended?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Ay.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Hark!--<Br/>Who lies i' the second chamber?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Donalbain.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>This is a sorry sight.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Looking on his hands.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>A foolish thought, to say a sorry sight.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>There's one did laugh in's sleep, and one cried, "Murder!"<Br/>That they did wake each other: I stood and heard them:<Br/>But
                  they did say their prayers, and address'd them<Br/>Again to sleep.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>There are two lodg'd together.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>One cried, "God bless us!" and, "Amen," the other;<Br/>As they had seen me with these hangman's hands.<Br/>Listening their fear,
                  I could not say "Amen,"<Br/>When they did say, "God bless us."</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Consider it not so deeply.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>But wherefore could not I pronounce "Amen"?<Br/>I had most need of blessing, and "Amen"<Br/>Stuck in my throat.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>These deeds must not be thought<Br/>After these ways; so, it will make us mad.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I heard a voice cry, "Sleep no more!<Br/>Macbeth does murder sleep,"--the innocent sleep;<Br/>Sleep that knits up the ravell'd
                  sleave of care,<Br/>The death of each day's life, sore labour's bath,<Br/>Balm of hurt minds, great nature's second
                  course,<Br/>Chief nourisher in life's feast.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>What do you mean?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Still it cried, "Sleep no more!" to all the house: "Glamis hath murder'd sleep, and therefore Cawdor<Br/>Shall sleep no
                  more,--Macbeth shall sleep no more!"</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Who was it that thus cried? Why, worthy thane,<Br/>You do unbend your noble strength to think<Br/>So brainsickly of things.--Go
                  get some water,<Br/>And wash this filthy witness from your hand.--<Br/>Why did you bring these daggers from the place?<Br/>They must
                  lie there: go carry them; and smear<Br/>The sleepy grooms with blood.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I'll go no more:<Br/>I am afraid to think what I have done;<Br/>Look on't again I dare not.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Infirm of purpose!<Br/>Give me the daggers: the sleeping and the dead<Br/>Are but as pictures: 'tis the eye of
                  childhood<Br/>That fears a painted devil. If he do bleed,<Br/>I'll gild the faces of the grooms withal,<Br/>For it must seem their
                  guilt.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="LADYMACBETH">Knocking within</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Whence is that knocking?<Br/>How is't with me, when every noise appals me?<Br/>What hands are here? Ha, they pluck out mine
                  eyes!<Br/>Will all great Neptune's ocean wash this blood<Br/>Clean from my hand? No; this my hand will rather<Br/>The multitudinous
                  seas incarnadine,<Br/>Making the green one red.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>My hands are of your color, but I shame<Br/>To wear a heart so white. <Instruction>Knocking within</Instruction> I hear
                  knocking<Br/>At the south entry:--retire we to our chamber.<Br/>A little water clears us of this deed:<Br/>How easy is it then! Your
                  constancy<Br/>Hath left you unattended.--<Instruction>Knocking within</Instruction> Hark, more knocking:<Br/>Get on your nightgown,
                  lest occasion call us<Br/>And show us to be watchers:--be not lost<Br/>So poorly in your thoughts.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>To know my deed, 'twere best not know myself. <Instruction>Knocking within</Instruction>
                  <Br/>Wake Duncan with thy knocking! I would thou couldst!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="PORTER">Knocking within</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="PORTER">
                <Text>Here's a knocking indeed! If a man were porter of hell-gate, he should have old turning the key.
                    <Instruction>Knocking</Instruction> Knock, knock, knock.<Br/>Who's there, i' the name of Belzebub? Here's a farmer that hanged
                  himself on the expectation of plenty: come in time; have napkins enow about you; here you'll sweat
                    for't.--<Instruction>Knocking</Instruction> Knock, knock! Who's there, in the other devil's name? Faith, here's an equivocator,
                  that could swear in both the scales against either scale, who committed treason enough for God's sake, yet could not equivocate to
                  heaven: O, come in, equivocator. <Instruction>Knocking</Instruction> Knock, knock, knock! Who's there? Faith, here's an English
                  tailor come hither, for stealing out of a French hose: come in, tailor; here you may roast your goose.--
                    <Instruction>Knocking</Instruction> Knock, knock: never at quiet! What are you?--But this place is too cold for hell.<Br/>I'll
                  devil-porter it no further: I had thought to have let in some of all professions, that go the primrose way to the everlasting
                  bonfire. <Instruction>Knocking</Instruction> Anon, anon! I pray you, remember the porter.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Opens the gate.</Instruction>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACDUFF LENNOX"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Was it so late, friend, ere you went to bed,<Br/>That you do lie so late?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="PORTER">
                <Text>Faith, sir, we were carousing till the second cock: and drink, sir, is a great provoker of three things.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>What three things does drink especially provoke?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="PORTER">
                <Text>Marry, sir, nose-painting, sleep, and urine. Lechery, sir, it provokes and unprovokes; it provokes the desire, but it takes away
                  the performance: therefore much drink may be said to be an equivocator with lechery: it makes him, and it mars him; it sets him on,
                  and it takes him off; it persuades him, and disheartens him; makes him stand to, and not stand to: in conclusion, equivocates him in
                  a sleep, and giving him the lie, leaves him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>I believe drink gave thee the lie last night.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="PORTER">
                <Text>That it did, sir, i' the very throat o' me; but I requited him for his lie; and, I think, being too strong for him, though he
                  took up my legs sometime, yet I made a shift to cast him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Is thy master stirring?--<Br/>Our knocking has awak'd him; here he comes.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Good morrow, noble sir!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Good morrow, both!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Is the king stirring, worthy thane?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Not yet.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>He did command me to call timely on him:<Br/>I have almost slipp'd the hour.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I'll bring you to him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>I know this is a joyful trouble to you;<Br/>But yet 'tis one.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>The labour we delight in physics pain.<Br/>This is the door.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>I'll make so bold to call.<Br/>For 'tis my limited service.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MACDUFF"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Goes the king hence to-day?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>He does: he did appoint so.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>The night has been unruly: where we lay,<Br/>Our chimneys were blown down: and, as they say,<Br/>Lamentings heard i' the air,
                  strange screams of death;<Br/>And prophesying, with accents terrible,<Br/>Of dire combustion and confus'd events,<Br/>New hatch'd to
                  the woeful time: the obscure bird<Br/>Clamour'd the live-long night; some say the earth<Br/>Was feverous, and did shake.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>'Twas a rough night.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>My young remembrance cannot parallel<Br/>A fellow to it.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACDUFF"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>O horror, horror, horror! Tongue nor heart<Br/>Cannot conceive nor name thee!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH LENNOX">
                <Text>What's the matter?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Confusion now hath made his masterpiece!<Br/>Most sacrilegious murder hath broke ope<Br/>The Lord's anointed temple, and stole
                  thence<Br/>The life o' the building.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>What is't you say? the life?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Mean you his majesty?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Approach the chamber, and destroy your sight<Br/>With a new Gorgon:--do not bid me speak;<Br/>See, and then speak
                  yourselves.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MACBETH LENNOX"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Awake, awake!--<Br/>Ring the alarum bell:--murder and treason!<Br/>Banquo and Donalbain! Malcolm! awake!<Br/>Shake off this
                  downy sleep, death's counterfeit,<Br/>And look on death itself! up, up, and see<Br/>The great doom's image! Malcolm! Banquo!<Br/>As
                  from your graves rise up, and walk like sprites<Br/>To countenance this horror!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Alarum-bell rings.</Instruction>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>What's the business,<Br/>That such a hideous trumpet calls to parley<Br/>The sleepers of the house? speak, speak!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>O gentle lady, 'Tis not for you to hear what I can speak:<Br/>The repetition, in a woman's ear,<Br/>Would murder as it
                  fell.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="BANQUO"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>O Banquo, Banquo!<Br/>Our royal master's murder'd!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Woe, alas!<Br/>What, in our house?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Too cruel any where.--<Br/>Dear Duff, I pr'ythee, contradict thyself,<Br/>And say it is not so.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH LENNOX ROSS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Had I but died an hour before this chance,<Br/>I had liv'd a blessed time; for, from this instant<Br/>There's nothing serious in
                  mortality:<Br/>All is but toys: renown and grace is dead;<Br/>The wine of life is drawn, and the mere lees<Br/>Is left this vault to
                  brag of.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MALCOLM DONALBAIN"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="DONALBAIN">
                <Text>What is amiss?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>You are, and do not know't:<Br/>The spring, the head, the fountain of your blood<Br/>Is stopp'd; the very source of it is
                  stopp'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Your royal father's murder'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>O, by whom?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Those of his chamber, as it seem'd, had done't:<Br/>Their hands and faces were all badg'd with blood;<Br/>So were their daggers,
                  which, unwip'd, we found<Br/>Upon their pillows:<Br/>They star'd, and were distracted; no man's life<Br/>Was to be trusted with
                  them.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>O, yet I do repent me of my fury,<Br/>That I did kill them.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Wherefore did you so?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Who can be wise, amaz'd, temperate, and furious,<Br/>Loyal and neutral, in a moment? No man:<Br/>The expedition of my violent
                  love<Br/>Outrun the pauser reason. Here lay Duncan,<Br/>His silver skin lac'd with his golden blood;<Br/>And his gash'd stabs look'd
                  like a breach in nature<Br/>For ruin's wasteful entrance: there, the murderers,<Br/>Steep'd in the colours of their trade, their
                  daggers<Br/>Unmannerly breech'd with gore: who could refrain,<Br/>That had a heart to love, and in that heart<Br/>Courage to make's
                  love known?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Help me hence, ho!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Look to the lady.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Why do we hold our tongues,<Br/>That most may claim this argument for ours?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DONALBAIN">
                <Text>What should be spoken here, where our fate,<Br/>Hid in an auger hole, may rush, and seize us?<Br/>Let's away;<Br/>Our tears are
                  not yet brew'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Nor our strong sorrow<Br/>Upon the foot of motion.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Look to the lady:--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="LADYMACBETH">Carried ou</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>And when we have our naked frailties hid,<Br/>That suffer in exposure, let us meet,<Br/>And question this most bloody piece of
                  work<Br/>To know it further. Fears and scruples shake us:<Br/>In the great hand of God I stand; and thence,<Br/>Against the
                  undivulg'd pretense I fight<Br/>Of treasonous malice.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>And so do I.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="#all">
                <Text>So all.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Let's briefly put on manly readiness,<Br/>And meet i' the hall together.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="#all">
                <Text>Well contented.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MACBETH MACDUFF BANQUO">All but Malcoln and Donalbain</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>What will you do? Let's not consort with them:<Br/>To show an unfelt sorrow is an office<Br/>Which the false man does easy. I'll
                  to England.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DONALBAIN">
                <Text>To Ireland, I; our separated fortune<Br/>Shall keep us both the safer: where we are,<Br/>There's daggers in men's smiles: the
                  near in blood,<Br/>The nearer bloody.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>This murderous shaft that's shot<Br/>Hath not yet lighted; and our safest way<Br/>Is to avoid the aim. Therefore to
                  horse;<Br/>And let us not be dainty of leave-taking,<Br/>But shift away: there's warrant in that theft<Br/>Which steals itself, when
                  there's no mercy left.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>

          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. Without the Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="ROSS OLDMAN"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="OLDMAN">
                <Text>Threescore and ten I can remember well:<Br/>Within the volume of which time I have seen<Br/>Hours dreadful and things strange;
                  but this sore night<Br/>Hath trifled former knowings.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Ah, good father,<Br/>Thou seest, the heavens, as troubled with man's act,<Br/>Threaten his bloody stage: by the clock 'tis
                  day,<Br/>And yet dark night strangles the travelling lamp;<Br/>Is't night's predominance, or the day's shame,<Br/>That darkness does
                  the face of earth entomb,<Br/>When living light should kiss it?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="OLDMAN">
                <Text>'Tis unnatural,<Br/>Even like the deed that's done. On Tuesday last,<Br/>A falcon, towering in her pride of place,<Br/>Was by a
                  mousing owl hawk'd at and kill'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>And Duncan's horses,--a thing most strange and certain,--<Br/>Beauteous and swift, the minions of their race,<Br/>Turn'd wild in
                  nature, broke their stalls, flung out,<Br/>Contending 'gainst obedience, as they would make<Br/>War with mankind.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="OLDMAN">
                <Text>'Tis said they eat each other.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>They did so; to the amazement of mine eyes,<Br/>That look'd upon't.<Br/>Here comes the good Macduff.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACDUFF"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Why, see you not?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Is't known who did this more than bloody deed?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Those that Macbeth hath slain.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Alas, the day!<Br/>What good could they pretend?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>They were suborn'd:<Br/>Malcolm and Donalbain, the king's two sons,<Br/>Are stol'n away and fled; which puts upon
                  them<Br/>Suspicion of the deed.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>'Gainst nature still:<Br/>Thriftless ambition, that wilt ravin up<Br/>Thine own life's means!--Then 'tis most like,<Br/>The
                  sovereignty will fall upon Macbeth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>He is already nam'd; and gone to Scone<Br/>To be invested.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Where is Duncan's body?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Carried to Colme-kill,<Br/>The sacred storehouse of his predecessors,<Br/>And guardian of their bones.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Will you to Scone?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>No, cousin, I'll to Fife.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Well, I will thither.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Well, may you see things well done there,--adieu!--<Br/>Lest our old robes sit easier than our new!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Farewell, father.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="OLDMAN">
                <Text>God's benison go with you; and with those<Br/>That would make good of bad, and friends of foes!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
        </Scenes>
      </Act>
      <Act>
        <Scenes>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Forres. A Room in the Palace.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="BANQUO"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Thou hast it now,--king, Cawdor, Glamis, all,<Br/>As the weird women promis'd; and, I fear,<Br/>Thou play'dst most foully for't;
                  yet it was said<Br/>It should not stand in thy posterity;<Br/>But that myself should be the root and father<Br/>Of many kings. If
                  there come truth from them,--<Br/>As upon thee, Macbeth, their speeches shine,--<Br/>Why, by the verities on thee made good,<Br/>May
                  they not be my oracles as well,<Br/>And set me up in hope? But hush; no more.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Sennet sounded.</Instruction>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH">As king</Entry>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH">As queen</Entry>
                <Entry role-ref="LENNOX ROSS BANQUO LORDS LADIES ATTENDANTS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Here's our chief guest.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>If he had been forgotten,<Br/>It had been as a gap in our great feast,<Br/>And all-thing unbecoming.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>To-night we hold a solemn supper, sir,<Br/>And I'll request your presence.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Let your highness<Br/>Command upon me; to the which my duties<Br/>Are with a most indissoluble tie<Br/>For ever knit.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Ride you this afternoon?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Ay, my good lord.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>We should have else desir'd your good advice,--<Br/>Which still hath been both grave and prosperous,--<Br/>In this day's
                  council; but we'll take to-morrow.<Br/>Is't far you ride?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>As far, my lord, as will fill up the time 'Twixt this and supper: go not my horse the better,<Br/>I must become a borrower of
                  the night,<Br/>For a dark hour or twain.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Fail not our feast.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>My lord, I will not.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>We hear our bloody cousins are bestow'd<Br/>In England and in Ireland; not confessing<Br/>Their cruel parricide, filling their
                  hearers<Br/>With strange invention: but of that to-morrow;<Br/>When therewithal we shall have cause of state<Br/>Craving us jointly.
                  Hie you to horse: adieu,<Br/>Till you return at night. Goes Fleance with you?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>Ay, my good lord: our time does call upon's.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I wish your horses swift and sure of foot;<Br/>And so I do commend you to their backs.<Br/>Farewell.--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="BANQUO"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Let every man be master of his time<Br/>Till seven at night; to make society<Br/>The sweeter welcome, we will keep
                  ourself<Br/>Till supper time alone: while then, God be with you!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="LADYMACBETH LORDS LADIES"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Sirrah, a word with you: attend those men<Br/>Our pleasure?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ATTENDANT">
                <Text>They are, my lord, without the palace gate.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Bring them before us.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="ATTENDANT"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>To be thus is nothing;<Br/>But to be safely thus:--our fears in Banquo.<Br/>Stick deep; and in his royalty of nature<Br/>Reigns
                  that which would be fear'd: 'tis much he dares;<Br/>And, to that dauntless temper of his mind,<Br/>He hath a wisdom that doth guide
                  his valour<Br/>To act in safety. There is none but he<Br/>Whose being I do fear: and under him,<Br/>My genius is rebuk'd; as, it is
                  said,<Br/>Mark Antony's was by Caesar. He chid the sisters<Br/>When first they put the name of king upon me,<Br/>And bade them speak
                  to him; then, prophet-like,<Br/>They hail'd him father to a line of kings:<Br/>Upon my head they plac'd a fruitless crown,<Br/>And
                  put a barren sceptre in my gripe,<Br/>Thence to be wrench'd with an unlineal hand,<Br/>No son of mine succeeding. If't be
                  so,<Br/>For Banquo's issue have I fil'd my mind;<Br/>For them the gracious Duncan have I murder'd;<Br/>Put rancours in the vessel of
                  my peace<Br/>Only for them; and mine eternal jewel<Br/>Given to the common enemy of man,<Br/>To make them kings, the seed of Banquo
                  kings!<Br/>Rather than so, come, fate, into the list,<Br/>And champion me to the utterance!--Who's there?--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="ATTENDANT FIRSTMURDERER SECONDMURDERER"/>
              </Entries>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="ATTENDANT"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>It was, so please your highness.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Well then, now<Br/>Have you consider'd of my speeches? Know<Br/>That it was he, in the times past, which held you<Br/>So under
                  fortune; which you thought had been<Br/>Our innocent self: this I made good to you<Br/>In our last conference, pass'd in probation
                  with you<Br/>How you were borne in hand, how cross'd, the instruments,<Br/>Who wrought with them, and all things else that
                  might<Br/>To half a soul and to a notion craz'd<Br/>Say, "Thus did Banquo."</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>You made it known to us.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I did so; and went further, which is now<Br/>Our point of second meeting. Do you find<Br/>Your patience so predominant in your
                  nature,<Br/>That you can let this go? Are you so gospell'd,<Br/>To pray for this good man and for his issue,<Br/>Whose heavy hand
                  hath bow'd you to the grave,<Br/>And beggar'd yours forever?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>We are men, my liege.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Ay, in the catalogue ye go for men;<Br/>As hounds, and greyhounds, mongrels, spaniels, curs,<Br/>Shoughs, water-rugs, and
                  demi-wolves are clept<Br/>All by the name of dogs: the valu'd file<Br/>Distinguishes the swift, the slow, the subtle,<Br/>The
                  house-keeper, the hunter, every one<Br/>According to the gift which bounteous nature<Br/>Hath in him clos'd; whereby he does
                  receive<Br/>Particular addition, from the bill<Br/>That writes them all alike: and so of men.<Br/>Now, if you have a station in the
                  file,<Br/>Not i' the worst rank of manhood, say it;<Br/>And I will put that business in your bosoms,<Br/>Whose execution takes your
                  enemy off;<Br/>Grapples you to the heart and love of us,<Br/>Who wear our health but sickly in his life,<Br/>Which in his death were
                  perfect.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDMURDERER">
                <Text>I am one, my liege,<Br/>Whom the vile blows and buffets of the world<Br/>Have so incens'd that I am reckless what<Br/>I do to
                  spite the world.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>And I another,<Br/>So weary with disasters, tugg'd with fortune,<Br/>That I would set my life on any chance,<Br/>To mend it or
                  be rid on't.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Both of you<Br/>Know Banquo was your enemy.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER SECONDMURDERER">
                <Text>True, my lord.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>So is he mine; and in such bloody distance,<Br/>That every minute of his being thrusts<Br/>Against my near'st of life; and
                  though I could<Br/>With barefac'd power sweep him from my sight,<Br/>And bid my will avouch it, yet I must not,<Br/>For certain
                  friends that are both his and mine,<Br/>Whose loves I may not drop, but wail his fall<Br/>Who I myself struck down: and thence it
                  is<Br/>That I to your assistance do make love;<Br/>Masking the business from the common eye<Br/>For sundry weighty reasons.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDMURDERER">
                <Text>We shall, my lord,<Br/>Perform what you command us.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Though our lives--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Your spirits shine through you. Within this hour at most,<Br/>I will advise you where to plant yourselves;<Br/>Acquaint you with
                  the perfect spy o' the time,<Br/>The moment on't; for't must be done to-night<Br/>And something from the palace; always
                  thought<Br/>That I require a clearness; and with him,--<Br/>To leave no rubs nor botches in the work,--<Br/>Fleance his son, that
                  keeps him company,<Br/>Whose absence is no less material to me<Br/>Than is his father's, must embrace the fate<Br/>Of that dark
                  hour. Resolve yourselves apart:<Br/>I'll come to you anon.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER SECONDMURDERER">
                <Text>We are resolv'd, my lord.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I'll call upon you straight: abide within.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER SECONDMURDERER"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>It is concluded:--Banquo, thy soul's flight,<Br/>If it find heaven, must find it out to-night.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. Another Room in the Palace.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH SERVANT"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Is Banquo gone from court?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SERVANT">
                <Text>Ay, madam, but returns again to-night.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Say to the king, I would attend his leisure<Br/>For a few words.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SERVANT">
                <Text>Madam, I will.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="SERVANT"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Naught's had, all's spent,<Br/>Where our desire is got without content: 'Tis safer to be that which we destroy,<Br/>Than, by
                  destruction, dwell in doubtful joy.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>How now, my lord! why do you keep alone,<Br/>Of sorriest fancies your companions making;<Br/>Using those thoughts which should
                  indeed have died<Br/>With them they think on? Things without all remedy<Br/>Should be without regard: what's done is done.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>We have scotch'd the snake, not kill'd it;<Br/>She'll close, and be herself; whilst our poor malice<Br/>Remains in danger of her
                  former tooth.<Br/>But let the frame of things disjoint,<Br/>Both the worlds suffer,<Br/>Ere we will eat our meal in fear, and
                  sleep<Br/>In the affliction of these terrible dreams<Br/>That shake us nightly: better be with the dead,<Br/>Whom we, to gain our
                  peace, have sent to peace,<Br/>Than on the torture of the mind to lie<Br/>In restless ecstasy. Duncan is in his grave;<Br/>After
                  life's fitful fever he sleeps well;<Br/>Treason has done his worst: nor steel, nor poison,<Br/>Malice domestic, foreign levy,
                  nothing,<Br/>Can touch him further.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Come on;<Br/>Gently my lord, sleek o'er your rugged looks;<Br/>Be bright and jovial 'mong your guests to-night.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>So shall I, love; and so, I pray, be you:<Br/>Let your remembrance apply to Banquo;<Br/>Present him eminence, both with eye and
                  tongue:<Br/>Unsafe the while, that we<Br/>Must lave our honors in these flattering streams;<Br/>And make our faces vizards to our
                  hearts,<Br/>Disguising what they are.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>You must leave this.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>O, full of scorpions is my mind, dear wife!<Br/>Thou know'st that Banquo, and his Fleance, lives.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>But in them nature's copy's not eterne.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>There's comfort yet; they are assailable;<Br/>Then be thou jocund: ere the bat hath flown<Br/>His cloister'd flight, ere to
                  black Hecate's summons,<Br/>The shard-borne beetle, with his drowsy hums,<Br/>Hath rung night's yawning peal, there shall be
                  done<Br/>A deed of dreadful note.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>What's to be done?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Be innocent of the knowledge, dearest chuck,<Br/>Till thou applaud the deed. Come, seeling night,<Br/>Scarf up the tender eye of
                  pitiful day;<Br/>And with thy bloody and invisible hand<Br/>Cancel and tear to pieces that great bond<Br/>Which keeps me
                  pale!--Light thickens; and the crow<Br/>Makes wing to the rooky wood:<Br/>Good things of day begin to droop and drowse;<Br/>Whiles
                  night's black agents to their preys do rouse.--<Br/>Thou marvell'st at my words: but hold thee still;<Br/>Things bad begun make
                  strong themselves by ill:<Br/>So, pr'ythee, go with me.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. A Park or Lawn, with a gate leading to the</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MURDERERS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>But who did bid thee join with us?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDMURDERER">
                <Text>Macbeth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDMURDERER">
                <Text>He needs not our mistrust; since he delivers<Br/>Our offices and what we have to do<Br/>To the direction just.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Then stand with us.<Br/>The west yet glimmers with some streaks of day:<Br/>Now spurs the lated traveller apace,<Br/>To gain the
                  timely inn; and near approaches<Br/>The subject of our watch.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDMURDERER">
                <Text>Hark! I hear horses.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO" offstage="1">
                <Text>Give us a light there, ho!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDMURDERER">
                <Text>Then 'tis he; the rest<Br/>That are within the note of expectation<Br/>Already are i' the court.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>His horses go about.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDMURDERER">
                <Text>Almost a mile; but he does usually,<Br/>So all men do, from hence to the palace gate<Br/>Make it their walk.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDMURDERER">
                <Text>A light, a light!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDMURDERER">
                <Text>'Tis he.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Stand to't.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="BANQUO FLEANCE">With a torch</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>It will be rain to-night.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Let it come down.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Assaults Banquo.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="BANQUO">
                <Text>O, treachery! Fly, good Fleance, fly, fly, fly!<Br/>Thou mayst revenge.--O slave!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Banquo dies.</Instruction>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="FLEANCE">Escapes</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDMURDERER">
                <Text>Who did strike out the light?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Was't not the way?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDMURDERER">
                <Text>There's but one down: the son is fled.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDMURDERER">
                <Text>We have lost best half of our affair.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Well, let's away, and say how much is done.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. A Room of state in the Palace. A banquet</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH LADYMACBETH ROSS LENNOX LORDS ATTENDANTS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>You know your own degrees: sit down. At first<Br/>And last the hearty welcome.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LORDS">
                <Text>Thanks to your majesty.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Ourself will mingle with society,<Br/>And play the humble host.<Br/>Our hostess keeps her state; but, in best time,<Br/>We will
                  require her welcome.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Pronounce it for me, sir, to all our friends;<Br/>For my heart speaks they are welcome.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>See, they encounter thee with their hearts' thanks.--<Br/>Both sides are even: here I'll sit i' the midst:</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">To the door</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Be large in mirth; anon we'll drink a measure<Br/>The table round.--There's blood upon thy face.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>'Tis Banquo's then.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>'Tis better thee without than he within.<Br/>Is he despatch'd?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>My lord, his throat is cut; that I did for him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Thou art the best o' the cut-throats; yet he's good<Br/>That did the like for Fleance: if thou didst it,<Br/>Thou art the
                  nonpareil.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Most royal sir,<Br/>Fleance is 'scap'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Then comes my fit again: I had else been perfect;<Br/>Whole as the marble, founded as the rock;<Br/>As broad and general as the
                  casing air:<Br/>But now I am cabin'd, cribb'd, confin'd, bound in<Br/>To saucy doubts and fears. But Banquo's safe?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Ay, my good lord: safe in a ditch he bides,<Br/>With twenty trenched gashes on his head;<Br/>The least a death to nature.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Thanks for that:<Br/>There the grown serpent lies; the worm that's fled<Br/>Hath nature that in time will venom breed,<Br/>No
                  teeth for the present.--Get thee gone; to-morrow<Br/>We'll hear, ourselves, again.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>My royal lord,<Br/>You do not give the cheer: the feast is sold<Br/>That is not often vouch'd, while 'tis a-making, 'Tis given
                  with welcome; to feed were best at home;<Br/>From thence the sauce to meat is ceremony;<Br/>Meeting were bare without it.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Sweet remembrancer!--<Br/>Now, good digestion wait on appetite,<Br/>And health on both!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>May't please your highness sit.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>The Ghost of Banquo rises, and sits in Macbeth's place.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Here had we now our country's honor roof'd,<Br/>Were the grac'd person of our Banquo present;<Br/>Who may I rather challenge for
                  unkindness<Br/>Than pity for mischance!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>His absence, sir,<Br/>Lays blame upon his promise. Please't your highness<Br/>To grace us with your royal company?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>The table's full.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Here is a place reserv'd, sir.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Where?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Here, my good lord. What is't that moves your highness?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Which of you have done this?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LORDS">
                <Text>What, my good lord?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Thou canst not say I did it: never shake<Br/>Thy gory locks at me.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Gentlemen, rise; his highness is not well.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Sit, worthy friends:--my lord is often thus,<Br/>And hath been from his youth: pray you, keep seat;<Br/>The fit is momentary;
                  upon a thought<Br/>He will again be well: if much you note him,<Br/>You shall offend him, and extend his passion:<Br/>Feed, and
                  regard him not.--Are you a man?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Ay, and a bold one, that dare look on that<Br/>Which might appal the devil.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>O proper stuff!<Br/>This is the very painting of your fear:<Br/>This is the air-drawn dagger which, you said,<Br/>Led you to
                  Duncan. O, these flaws, and starts,--<Br/>Impostors to true fear,--would well become<Br/>A woman's story at a winter's
                  fire,<Br/>Authoriz'd by her grandam. Shame itself!<Br/>Why do you make such faces? When all's done,<Br/>You look but on a
                  stool.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Pr'ythee, see there! behold! look! lo! how say you?--<Br/>Why, what care I? If thou canst nod, speak too.--<Br/>If charnel
                  houses and our graves must send<Br/>Those that we bury back, our monuments<Br/>Shall be the maws of kites.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Ghost disappears.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>What, quite unmann'd in folly?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>If I stand here, I saw him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Fie, for shame!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Blood hath been shed ere now, i' the olden time,<Br/>Ere humane statute purg'd the gentle weal;<Br/>Ay, and since too, murders
                  have been perform'd<Br/>Too terrible for the ear: the time has been,<Br/>That, when the brains were out, the man would die,<Br/>And
                  there an end; but now they rise again,<Br/>With twenty mortal murders on their crowns,<Br/>And push us from our stools: this is more
                  strange<Br/>Than such a murder is.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>My worthy lord,<Br/>Your noble friends do lack you.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I do forget:--<Br/>Do not muse at me, my most worthy friends;<Br/>I have a strange infirmity, which is nothing<Br/>To those that
                  know me. Come, love and health to all;<Br/>Then I'll sit down.--Give me some wine, fill full.--<Br/>I drink to the general joy o'
                  the whole table,<Br/>And to our dear friend Banquo, whom we miss:<Br/>Would he were here! to all, and him, we thirst,<Br/>And all to
                  all.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LORDS">
                <Text>Our duties, and the pledge.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Ghost rises again.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Avaunt! and quit my sight! let the earth hide thee!<Br/>Thy bones are marrowless, thy blood is cold;<Br/>Thou hast no
                  speculation in those eyes<Br/>Which thou dost glare with!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Think of this, good peers,<Br/>But as a thing of custom: 'tis no other,<Br/>Only it spoils the pleasure of the time.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>What man dare, I dare:<Br/>Approach thou like the rugged Russian bear,<Br/>The arm'd rhinoceros, or the Hyrcan tiger;<Br/>Take
                  any shape but that, and my firm nerves<Br/>Shall never tremble: or be alive again,<Br/>And dare me to the desert with thy
                  sword;<Br/>If trembling I inhabit then, protest me<Br/>The baby of a girl. Hence, horrible shadow!<Br/>Unreal mockery, hence!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Ghost disappears.</Instruction>
              <Notes>
                <Note>Why, so;--being gone,<Br/>I am a man again.--Pray you, sit still.</Note>
              </Notes>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>You have displaced the mirth, broke the good meeting,<Br/>With most admir'd disorder.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Can such things be,<Br/>And overcome us like a summer's cloud,<Br/>Without our special wonder? You make me strange<Br/>Even to
                  the disposition that I owe,<Br/>When now I think you can behold such sights,<Br/>And keep the natural ruby of your cheeks,<Br/>When
                  mine are blanch'd with fear.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>What sights, my lord?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>I pray you, speak not; he grows worse and worse;<Br/>Question enrages him: at once, good-night:--<Br/>Stand not upon the order
                  of your going,<Br/>But go at once.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Good-night; and better health<Br/>Attend his majesty!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>A kind good-night to all!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="LENNOX ROSS LORDS"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>It will have blood; they say, blood will have blood:<Br/>Stones have been known to move, and trees to speak;<Br/>Augurs, and
                  understood relations, have<Br/>By magot-pies, and choughs, and rooks, brought forth<Br/>The secret'st man of blood.--What is the
                  night?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Almost at odds with morning, which is which.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>How say'st thou, that Macduff denies his person<Br/>At our great bidding?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Did you send to him, sir?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I hear it by the way; but I will send:<Br/>There's not a one of them but in his house<Br/>I keep a servant fee'd. I will
                  to-morrow, (And betimes I will) to the weird sisters:<Br/>More shall they speak; for now I am bent to know,<Br/>By the worst means,
                  the worst. For mine own good,<Br/>All causes shall give way: I am in blood<Br/>Step't in so far that, should I wade no
                  more,<Br/>Returning were as tedious as go o'er:<Br/>Strange things I have in head, that will to hand;<Br/>Which must be acted ere
                  they may be scann'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>You lack the season of all natures, sleep.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Come, we'll to sleep. My strange and self-abuse<Br/>Is the initiate fear that wants hard use:--<Br/>We are yet but young in
                  deed.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The heath. Thunder.</LocationDescription>
              <StartPresences>
                <StartPresence role-ref="HECATE"/>
              </StartPresences>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="THREEWITCHES"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Why, how now, Hecate? you look angerly.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="HECATE">
                <Text>Have I not reason, beldams as you are,<Br/>Saucy and overbold? How did you dare<Br/>To trade and traffic with Macbeth<Br/>In
                  riddles and affairs of death;<Br/>And I, the mistress of your charms,<Br/>The close contriver of all harms,<Br/>Was never call'd to
                  bear my part,<Br/>Or show the glory of our art?<Br/>And, which is worse, all you have done<Br/>Hath been but for a wayward
                  son,<Br/>Spiteful and wrathful; who, as others do,<Br/>Loves for his own ends, not for you.<Br/>But make amends now: get you
                  gone,<Br/>And at the pit of Acheron<Br/>Meet me i' the morning: thither he<Br/>Will come to know his destiny.<Br/>Your vessels and
                  your spells provide,<Br/>Your charms, and everything beside.<Br/>I am for the air; this night I'll spend<Br/>Unto a dismal and a
                  fatal end.<Br/>Great business must be wrought ere noon:<Br/>Upon the corner of the moon<Br/>There hangs a vaporous drop
                  profound;<Br/>I'll catch it ere it come to ground:<Br/>And that, distill'd by magic sleights,<Br/>Shall raise such artificial
                  sprites,<Br/>As, by the strength of their illusion,<Br/>Shall draw him on to his confusion:<Br/>He shall spurn fate, scorn death,
                  and bear<Br/>His hopes 'bove wisdom, grace, and fear:<Br/>And you all know, security<Br/>Is mortals' chiefest enemy.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Music and song within, "Come away, come away" &amp;c.</Instruction>
              <Notes>
                <Note>Hark! I am call'd; my little spirit, see,<Br/>Sits in a foggy cloud and stays for me.</Note>
              </Notes>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="HECATE"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Come, let's make haste; she'll soon be back again.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Forres. A Room in the Palace.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LENNOX LORD"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>My former speeches have but hit your thoughts,<Br/>Which can interpret further: only, I say,<Br/>Thing's have been strangely
                  borne. The gracious Duncan<Br/>Was pitied of Macbeth:--marry, he was dead:--<Br/>And the right valiant Banquo walk'd too
                  late;<Br/>Whom, you may say, if't please you, Fleance kill'd,<Br/>For Fleance fled. Men must not walk too late.<Br/>Who cannot want
                  the thought, how monstrous<Br/>It was for Malcolm and for Donalbain<Br/>To kill their gracious father? damned fact!<Br/>How it did
                  grieve Macbeth! did he not straight,<Br/>In pious rage, the two delinquents tear<Br/>That were the slaves of drink and thralls of
                  sleep?<Br/>Was not that nobly done? Ay, and wisely too;<Br/>For 'twould have anger'd any heart alive,<Br/>To hear the men deny't. So
                  that, I say,<Br/>He has borne all things well: and I do think,<Br/>That had he Duncan's sons under his key,--<Br/>As, an't please
                  heaven, he shall not,--they should find<Br/>What 'twere to kill a father; so should Fleance.<Br/>But, peace!--for from broad words,
                  and 'cause he fail'd<Br/>His presence at the tyrant's feast, I hear,<Br/>Macduff lives in disgrace. Sir, can you tell<Br/>Where he
                  bestows himself?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LORD">
                <Text>The son of Duncan,<Br/>From whom this tyrant holds the due of birth,<Br/>Lives in the English court and is receiv'd<Br/>Of the
                  most pious Edward with such grace<Br/>That the malevolence of fortune nothing<Br/>Takes from his high respect: thither
                  Macduff<Br/>Is gone to pray the holy king, upon his aid<Br/>To wake Northumberland, and warlike Siward:<Br/>That, by the help of
                  these,--with Him above<Br/>To ratify the work,--we may again<Br/>Give to our tables meat, sleep to our nights;<Br/>Free from our
                  feasts and banquets bloody knives;<Br/>Do faithful homage, and receive free honours,--<Br/>All which we pine for now: and this
                  report<Br/>Hath so exasperate the king that he<Br/>Prepares for some attempt of war.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Sent he to Macduff?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LORD">
                <Text>He did: and with an absolute "Sir, not I,"<Br/>The cloudy messenger turns me his back,<Br/>And hums, as who should say, "You'll
                  rue the time<Br/>That clogs me with this answer."</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>And that well might<Br/>Advise him to a caution, to hold what distance<Br/>His wisdom can provide. Some holy angel<Br/>Fly to
                  the court of England, and unfold<Br/>His message ere he come; that a swift blessing<Br/>May soon return to this our suffering
                  country<Br/>Under a hand accurs'd!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LORD">
                <Text>I'll send my prayers with him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
        </Scenes>
      </Act>
      <Act>
        <Scenes>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>A dark Cave. In the middle, a Caldron Boiling. Thunder.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="THREEWITCHES"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Thrice the brinded cat hath mew'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Thrice; and once the hedge-pig whin'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>Harpier cries:--"tis time, 'tis time.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Round about the caldron go;<Br/>In the poison'd entrails throw.--<Br/>Toad, that under cold stone,<Br/>Days and nights has
                  thirty-one<Br/>Swelter'd venom sleeping got,<Br/>Boil thou first i' the charmed pot!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="#all">
                <Text>Double, double, toil and trouble;<Br/>Fire, burn; and caldron, bubble.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Fillet of a fenny snake,<Br/>In the caldron boil and bake;<Br/>Eye of newt, and toe of frog,<Br/>Wool of bat, and tongue of
                  dog,<Br/>Adder's fork, and blind-worm's sting,<Br/>Lizard's leg, and howlet's wing,--<Br/>For a charm of powerful trouble,<Br/>Like
                  a hell-broth boil and bubble.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="#all">
                <Text>Double, double, toil and trouble;<Br/>Fire, burn; and caldron, bubble.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>Scale of dragon, tooth of wolf,<Br/>Witch's mummy, maw and gulf<Br/>Of the ravin'd salt-sea shark,<Br/>Root of hemlock digg'd i'
                  the dark,<Br/>Liver of blaspheming Jew,<Br/>Gall of goat, and slips of yew<Br/>Sliver'd in the moon's eclipse,<Br/>Nose of Turk, and
                  Tartar's lips,<Br/>Finger of birth-strangl'd babe<Br/>Ditch-deliver'd by a drab,--<Br/>Make the gruel thick and slab:<Br/>Add
                  thereto a tiger's chaudron,<Br/>For the ingredients of our caldron.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="#all">
                <Text>Double, double, toil and trouble;<Br/>Fire, burn; and caldron, bubble.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Cool it with a baboon's blood,<Br/>Then the charm is firm and good.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="HECATE"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="HECATE">
                <Text>O, well done! I commend your pains;<Br/>And everyone shall share i' the gains.<Br/>And now about the cauldron sing,<Br/>Like
                  elves and fairies in a ring,<Br/>Enchanting all that you put in. <Br/>
                  <Instruction>Song</Instruction> Black spirits and white, red spirits and gray;<Br/>Mingle, mingle, mingle, you that mingle may.
                </Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="HECATE"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>By the pricking of my thumbs,<Br/>Something wicked this way comes:--<Br/>Open, locks, whoever knocks!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>How now, you secret, black, and midnight hags!<Br/>What is't you do?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THREEWITCHES">
                <Text>A deed without a name.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I conjure you, by that which you profess,--<Br/>Howe'er you come to know it,--answer me:<Br/>Though you untie the winds, and let
                  them fight<Br/>Against the churches; though the yesty waves<Br/>Confound and swallow navigation up;<Br/>Though bladed corn be
                  lodg'd, and trees blown down;<Br/>Though castles topple on their warders' heads;<Br/>Though palaces and pyramids do slope<Br/>Their
                  heads to their foundations; though the treasure<Br/>Of nature's germins tumble all together,<Br/>Even till destruction
                  sicken,--answer me<Br/>To what I ask you.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Speak.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Demand.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>We'll answer.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Say, if thou'dst rather hear it from our mouths,<Br/>Or from our masters?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Call 'em, let me see 'em.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Pour in sow's blood, that hath eaten<Br/>Her nine farrow; grease that's sweaten<Br/>From the murderer's gibbet throw<Br/>Into
                  the flame.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THREEWITCHES">
                <Text>Come, high or low;<Br/>Thyself and office deftly show!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="APPARITION">Thunder. An Apparition of an armed Head rises.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Tell me, thou unknown power,--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>He knows thy thought:<Br/>Hear his speech, but say thou naught.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="APPARITION">
                <Text>Macbeth! Macbeth! Macbeth! Beware Macduff;<Br/>Beware the Thane of Fife.--Dismiss me:--enough.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="APPARITION">Descends.</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Whate'er thou art, for thy good caution, thanks;<Br/>Thou hast harp'd my fear aright:--but one word more,--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>He will not be commanded: here's another,<Br/>More potent than the first.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="APPARITION">Thunder. An Apparition of a bloody child rises.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="APPARITION">
                <Text>Macbeth! Macbeth! Macbeth!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Had I three ears, I'd hear thee.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="APPARITION">
                <Text>Be bloody, bold, and resolute; laugh to scorn<Br/>The power of man, for none of woman born<Br/>Shall harm Macbeth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="APPARITION">Descends.</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Then live, Macduff: what need I fear of thee?<Br/>But yet I'll make assurance double sure,<Br/>And take a bond of fate: thou
                  shalt not live;<Br/>That I may tell pale-hearted fear it lies,<Br/>And sleep in spite of thunder.--What is this,</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="APPARITION">Thunder. An Apparition of a Child crowned, with a tree in his hand, rises.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>That rises like the issue of a king,<Br/>And wears upon his baby brow the round<Br/>And top of sovereignty?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THREEWITCHES">
                <Text>Listen, but speak not to't.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="APPARITION">
                <Text>Be lion-mettled, proud; and take no care<Br/>Who chafes, who frets, or where conspirers are:<Br/>Macbeth shall never vanquish'd
                  be, until<Br/>Great Birnam wood to high Dunsinane hill<Br/>Shall come against him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="APPARITION">Descends.</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>That will never be:<Br/>Who can impress the forest; bid the tree<Br/>Unfix his earth-bound root? Sweet bodements,
                  good!<Br/>Rebellion's head, rise never till the wood<Br/>Of Birnam rise, and our high-plac'd Macbeth<Br/>Shall live the lease of
                  nature, pay his breath<Br/>To time and mortal custom.--Yet my heart<Br/>Throbs to know one thing: tell me,--if your art<Br/>Can tell
                  so much,--shall Banquo's issue ever<Br/>Reign in this kingdom?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THREEWITCHES">
                <Text>Seek to know no more.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I will be satisfied: deny me this,<Br/>And an eternal curse fall on you! Let me know:--<Br/>Why sinks that cauldron? and what
                  noise is this?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Hautboys.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Show!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SECONDWITCH">
                <Text>Show!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THIRDWITCH">
                <Text>Show!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="THREEWITCHES">
                <Text>Show his eyes, and grieve his heart;<Br/>Come like shadows, so depart!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Eight kings appear, and pass over in order, the last with a glass in his hand; Banquo following.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Thou are too like the spirit of Banquo; down!<Br/>Thy crown does sear mine eyeballs:--and thy hair,<Br/>Thou other gold-bound
                  brow, is like the first;--<Br/>A third is like the former.--Filthy hags!<Br/>Why do you show me this?--A fourth!--Start,
                  eyes!<Br/>What, will the line stretch out to the crack of doom?<Br/>Another yet!--A seventh!--I'll see no more:--<Br/>And yet the
                  eighth appears, who bears a glass<Br/>Which shows me many more; and some I see<Br/>That twofold balls and treble sceptres
                  carry:<Br/>Horrible sight!--Now I see 'tis true;<Br/>For the blood-bolter'd Banquo smiles upon me,<Br/>And points at them for
                  his.--What! is this so?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTWITCH">
                <Text>Ay, sir, all this is so:--but why<Br/>Stands Macbeth thus amazedly?--<Br/>Come,sisters, cheer we up his sprites,<Br/>And show
                  the best of our delights;<Br/>I'll charm the air to give a sound,<Br/>While you perform your antic round;<Br/>That this great king
                  may kindly say,<Br/>Our duties did his welcome pay.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Music. The Witches dance.</Instruction>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="THREEWITCHES">Vanish.</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Where are they? Gone?--Let this pernicious hour<Br/>Stand aye accursed in the calendar!--<Br/>Come in, without there!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LENNOX"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>What's your grace's will?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Saw you the weird sisters?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>No, my lord.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Came they not by you?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>No indeed, my lord.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Infected be the air whereon they ride;<Br/>And damn'd all those that trust them!--I did hear<Br/>The galloping of horse: who
                  was't came by?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>'Tis two or three, my lord, that bring you word<Br/>Macduff is fled to England.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Fled to England!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Ay, my good lord.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Time, thou anticipat'st my dread exploits:<Br/>The flighty purpose never is o'ertook<Br/>Unless the deed go with it: from this
                  moment<Br/>The very firstlings of my heart shall be<Br/>The firstlings of my hand. And even now,<Br/>To crown my thoughts with acts,
                  be it thought and done:<Br/>The castle of Macduff I will surprise;<Br/>Seize upon Fife; give to the edge o' the sword<Br/>His wife,
                  his babes, and all unfortunate souls<Br/>That trace him in his line. No boasting like a fool;<Br/>This deed I'll do before this
                  purpose cool:<Br/>But no more sights!--Where are these gentlemen?<Br/>Come, bring me where they are.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Fife. A Room in Macduff's Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACDUFF SONOFMACDUFF ROSS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>What had he done, to make him fly the land?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>You must have patience, madam.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>He had none:<Br/>His flight was madness: when our actions do not,<Br/>Our fears do make us traitors.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>You know not<Br/>Whether it was his wisdom or his fear.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Wisdom! to leave his wife, to leave his babes,<Br/>His mansion, and his titles, in a place<Br/>From whence himself does fly? He
                  loves us not:<Br/>He wants the natural touch; for the poor wren,<Br/>The most diminutive of birds, will fight,<Br/>Her young ones in
                  her nest, against the owl.<Br/>All is the fear, and nothing is the love;<Br/>As little is the wisdom, where the flight<Br/>So runs
                  against all reason.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>My dearest coz,<Br/>I pray you, school yourself: but, for your husband,<Br/>He is noble, wise, Judicious, and best knows<Br/>The
                  fits o' the season. I dare not speak much further:<Br/>But cruel are the times, when we are traitors,<Br/>And do not know ourselves;
                  when we hold rumour<Br/>From what we fear, yet know not what we fear,<Br/>But float upon a wild and violent sea<Br/>Each way and
                  move.--I take my leave of you:<Br/>Shall not be long but I'll be here again:<Br/>Things at the worst will cease, or else climb
                  upward<Br/>To what they were before.--My pretty cousin,<Br/>Blessing upon you!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Father'd he is, and yet he's fatherless.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>I am so much a fool, should I stay longer,<Br/>It would be my disgrace and your discomfort:<Br/>I take my leave at once.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="ROSS"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Sirrah, your father's dead;<Br/>And what will you do now? How will you live?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>As birds do, mother.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>What, with worms and flies?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>With what I get, I mean; and so do they.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Poor bird! thou'dst never fear the net nor lime,<Br/>The pit-fall nor the gin.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>Why should I, mother? Poor birds they are not set for.<Br/>My father is not dead, for all your saying.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Yes, he is dead: how wilt thou do for father?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>Nay, how will you do for a husband?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Why, I can buy me twenty at any market.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>Then you'll buy 'em to sell again.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Thou speak'st with all thy wit; and yet, i' faith,<Br/>With wit enough for thee.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>Was my father a traitor, mother?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Ay, that he was.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>What is a traitor?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Why, one that swears and lies.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>And be all traitors that do so?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Everyone that does so is a traitor, and must be hanged.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>And must they all be hanged that swear and lie?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Every one.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>Who must hang them?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Why, the honest men.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>Then the liars and swearers are fools: for there are liars and swearers enow to beat the honest men and hang up them.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Now, God help thee, poor monkey! But how wilt thou do for a father?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>If he were dead, you'ld weep for him: if you would not, it were a good sign that I should quickly have a new father.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Poor prattler, how thou talk'st!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MESSENGER"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MESSENGER">
                <Text>Bless you, fair dame! I am not to you known,<Br/>Though in your state of honor I am perfect.<Br/>I doubt some danger does
                  approach you nearly:<Br/>If you will take a homely man's advice,<Br/>Be not found here; hence, with your little ones.<Br/>To fright
                  you thus, methinks, I am too savage;<Br/>To do worse to you were fell cruelty,<Br/>Which is too nigh your person. Heaven preserve
                  you!<Br/>I dare abide no longer.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MESSENGER"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>Whither should I fly?<Br/>I have done no harm. But I remember now<Br/>I am in this earthly world; where to do harm<Br/>Is often
                  laudable; to do good sometime<Br/>Accounted dangerous folly: why then, alas,<Br/>Do I put up that womanly defence,<Br/>To say I have
                  done no harm?--What are these faces?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MURDERERS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>Where is your husband?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">
                <Text>I hope, in no place so unsanctified<Br/>Where such as thou mayst find him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>He's a traitor.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>Thou liest, thou shag-haar'd villain!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FIRSTMURDERER">
                <Text>What, you egg!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Stabbing him.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="SONOFMACDUFF">
                <Text>He has kill'd me, mother:<Br/>Run away, I pray you!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Dies.</Instruction>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="LADYMACDUFF">Crying Murder, and pursued by the murderers.</Exit>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>England. Before the King's Palace.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MALCOLM MACDUFF"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Let us seek out some desolate shade and there<Br/>Weep our sad bosoms empty.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Let us rather<Br/>Hold fast the mortal sword, and, like good men,<Br/>Bestride our down-fall'n birthdom: each new morn<Br/>New
                  widows howl; new orphans cry; new sorrows<Br/>Strike heaven on the face, that it resounds<Br/>As if it felt with Scotland, and
                  yell'd out<Br/>Like syllable of dolour.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>What I believe, I'll wail;<Br/>What know, believe; and what I can redress,<Br/>As I shall find the time to friend, I
                  will.<Br/>What you have spoke, it may be so perchance.<Br/>This tyrant, whose sole name blisters our tongues,<Br/>Was once thought
                  honest: you have loved him well;<Br/>He hath not touch'd you yet. I am young; but something<Br/>You may deserve of him through me;
                  and wisdom<Br/>To offer up a weak, poor, innocent lamb<Br/>To appease an angry god.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>I am not treacherous.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>But Macbeth is.<Br/>A good and virtuous nature may recoil<Br/>In an imperial charge. But I shall crave your pardon;<Br/>That
                  which you are, my thoughts cannot transpose;<Br/>Angels are bright still, though the brightest fell:<Br/>Though all things foul
                  would wear the brows of grace,<Br/>Yet grace must still look so.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>I have lost my hopes.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Perchance even there where I did find my doubts.<Br/>Why in that rawness left you wife and child,--<Br/>Those precious motives,
                  those strong knots of love,--<Br/>Without leave-taking?--I pray you,<Br/>Let not my jealousies be your dishonors,<Br/>But mine own
                  safeties:--you may be rightly just,<Br/>Whatever I shall think.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Bleed, bleed, poor country!<Br/>Great tyranny, lay thou thy basis sure,<Br/>For goodness dare not check thee! wear thou thy
                  wrongs,<Br/>The title is affeer'd.--Fare thee well, lord:<Br/>I would not be the villain that thou think'st<Br/>For the whole space
                  that's in the tyrant's grasp<Br/>And the rich East to boot.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Be not offended:<Br/>I speak not as in absolute fear of you.<Br/>I think our country sinks beneath the yoke;<Br/>It weeps, it
                  bleeds; and each new day a gash<Br/>Is added to her wounds. I think, withal,<Br/>There would be hands uplifted in my right;<Br/>And
                  here, from gracious England, have I offer<Br/>Of goodly thousands: but, for all this,<Br/>When I shall tread upon the tyrant's
                  head,<Br/>Or wear it on my sword, yet my poor country<Br/>Shall have more vices than it had before;<Br/>More suffer, and more sundry
                  ways than ever,<Br/>By him that shall succeed.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>What should he be?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>It is myself I mean: in whom I know<Br/>All the particulars of vice so grafted<Br/>That, when they shall be open'd, black
                  Macbeth<Br/>Will seem as pure as snow; and the poor state<Br/>Esteem him as a lamb, being compar'd<Br/>With my confineless
                  harms.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Not in the legions<Br/>Of horrid hell can come a devil more damn'd<Br/>In evils to top Macbeth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>I grant him bloody,<Br/>Luxurious, avaricious, false, deceitful,<Br/>Sudden, malicious, smacking of every sin<Br/>That has a
                  name: but there's no bottom, none,<Br/>In my voluptuousness: your wives, your daughters,<Br/>Your matrons, and your maids, could not
                  fill up<Br/>The cistern of my lust; and my desire<Br/>All continent impediments would o'erbear,<Br/>That did oppose my will: better
                  Macbeth<Br/>Than such an one to reign.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Boundless intemperance<Br/>In nature is a tyranny; it hath been<Br/>The untimely emptying of the happy throne,<Br/>And fall of
                  many kings. But fear not yet<Br/>To take upon you what is yours: you may<Br/>Convey your pleasures in a spacious plenty,<Br/>And yet
                  seem cold, the time you may so hoodwink.<Br/>We have willing dames enough; there cannot be<Br/>That vulture in you, to devour so
                  many<Br/>As will to greatness dedicate themselves,<Br/>Finding it so inclin'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>With this there grows,<Br/>In my most ill-compos'd affection, such<Br/>A stanchless avarice, that, were I king,<Br/>I should cut
                  off the nobles for their lands;<Br/>Desire his jewels, and this other's house:<Br/>And my more-having would be as a sauce<Br/>To
                  make me hunger more; that I should forge<Br/>Quarrels unjust against the good and loyal,<Br/>Destroying them for wealth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>This avarice<Br/>Sticks deeper; grows with more pernicious root<Br/>Than summer-seeming lust; and it hath been<Br/>The sword of
                  our slain kings: yet do not fear;<Br/>Scotland hath foysons to fill up your will,<Br/>Of your mere own: all these are
                  portable,<Br/>With other graces weigh'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>But I have none: the king-becoming graces,<Br/>As justice, verity, temperance, stableness,<Br/>Bounty, perseverance, mercy,
                  lowliness,<Br/>Devotion, patience, courage, fortitude,<Br/>I have no relish of them; but abound<Br/>In the division of each several
                  crime,<Br/>Acting it many ways. Nay, had I power, I should<Br/>Pour the sweet milk of concord into hell,<Br/>Uproar the universal
                  peace, confound<Br/>All unity on earth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>O Scotland, Scotland!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>If such a one be fit to govern, speak:<Br/>I am as I have spoken.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Fit to govern!<Br/>No, not to live!--O nation miserable,<Br/>With an untitled tyrant bloody-scepter'd,<Br/>When shalt thou see
                  thy wholesome days again,<Br/>Since that the truest issue of thy throne<Br/>By his own interdiction stands accurs'd<Br/>And does
                  blaspheme his breed?--Thy royal father<Br/>Was a most sainted king; the queen that bore thee,<Br/>Oftener upon her knees than on her
                  feet,<Br/>Died every day she lived. Fare-thee-well!<Br/>These evils thou repeat'st upon thyself<Br/>Have banish'd me from
                  Scotland.--O my breast,<Br/>Thy hope ends here!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Macduff, this noble passion,<Br/>Child of integrity, hath from my soul<Br/>Wiped the black scruples, reconcil'd my
                  thoughts<Br/>To thy good truth and honour. Devilish Macbeth<Br/>By many of these trains hath sought to win me<Br/>Into his power;
                  and modest wisdom plucks me<Br/>From over-credulous haste: but God above<Br/>Deal between thee and me! for even now<Br/>I put myself
                  to thy direction, and<Br/>Unspeak mine own detraction; here abjure<Br/>The taints and blames I laid upon myself,<Br/>For strangers
                  to my nature. I am yet<Br/>Unknown to woman; never was forsworn;<Br/>Scarcely have coveted what was mine own;<Br/>At no time broke
                  my faith; would not betray<Br/>The devil to his fellow; and delight<Br/>No less in truth than life: my first false speaking<Br/>Was
                  this upon myself:--what I am truly,<Br/>Is thine and my poor country's to command:<Br/>Whither, indeed, before thy
                  here-approach,<Br/>Old Siward, with ten thousand warlike men<Br/>Already at a point, was setting forth:<Br/>Now we'll together; and
                  the chance of goodness<Br/>Be like our warranted quarrel! Why are you silent?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Such welcome and unwelcome things at once 'Tis hard to reconcile.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="DOCTOR"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Well; more anon.--Comes the king forth, I pray you?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Ay, sir: there are a crew of wretched souls<Br/>That stay his cure: their malady convinces<Br/>The great assay of art; but, at
                  his touch,<Br/>Such sanctity hath heaven given his hand,<Br/>They presently amend.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>I thank you, doctor.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="DOCTOR"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>What's the disease he means?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>'Tis call'd the evil:<Br/>A most miraculous work in this good king;<Br/>Which often, since my here-remain in England,<Br/>I have
                  seen him do. How he solicits heaven,<Br/>Himself best knows: but strangely-visited people,<Br/>All swoln and ulcerous, pitiful to
                  the eye,<Br/>The mere despair of surgery, he cures;<Br/>Hanging a golden stamp about their necks,<Br/>Put on with holy prayers: and
                  'tis spoken,<Br/>To the succeeding royalty he leaves<Br/>The healing benediction. With this strange virtue,<Br/>He hath a heavenly
                  gift of prophecy;<Br/>And sundry blessings hang about his throne,<Br/>That speak him full of grace.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>See, who comes here?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>My countryman; but yet I know him not.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="ROSS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>My ever-gentle cousin, welcome hither.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>I know him now. Good God, betimes remove<Br/>The means that makes us strangers!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Sir, amen.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Stands Scotland where it did?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Alas, poor country,--<Br/>Almost afraid to know itself! It cannot<Br/>Be call'd our mother, but our grave: where
                  nothing,<Br/>But who knows nothing, is once seen to smile;<Br/>Where sighs, and groans, and shrieks, that rent the air,<Br/>Are
                  made, not mark'd; where violent sorrow seems<Br/>A modern ecstasy; the dead man's knell<Br/>Is there scarce ask'd for who; and good
                  men's lives<Br/>Expire before the flowers in their caps,<Br/>Dying or ere they sicken.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>O, relation<Br/>Too nice, and yet too true!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>What's the newest grief?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>That of an hour's age doth hiss the speaker;<Br/>Each minute teems a new one.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>How does my wife?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Why, well.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>And all my children?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Well too.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>The tyrant has not batter'd at their peace?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>No; they were well at peace when I did leave 'em.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Be not a niggard of your speech: how goes't?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>When I came hither to transport the tidings,<Br/>Which I have heavily borne, there ran a rumour<Br/>Of many worthy fellows that
                  were out;<Br/>Which was to my belief witness'd the rather,<Br/>For that I saw the tyrant's power a-foot:<Br/>Now is the time of
                  help; your eye in Scotland<Br/>Would create soldiers, make our women fight,<Br/>To doff their dire distresses.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Be't their comfort<Br/>We are coming thither: gracious England hath<Br/>Lent us good Siward and ten thousand men;<Br/>An older
                  and a better soldier none<Br/>That Christendom gives out.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Would I could answer<Br/>This comfort with the like! But I have words<Br/>That would be howl'd out in the desert air,<Br/>Where
                  hearing should not latch them.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>What concern they?<Br/>The general cause? or is it a fee-grief<Br/>Due to some single breast?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>No mind that's honest<Br/>But in it shares some woe; though the main part<Br/>Pertains to you alone.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>If it be mine,<Br/>Keep it not from me, quickly let me have it.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Let not your ears despise my tongue for ever,<Br/>Which shall possess them with the heaviest sound<Br/>That ever yet they
                  heard.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Humh! I guess at it.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Your castle is surpris'd; your wife and babes<Br/>Savagely slaughter'd: to relate the manner<Br/>Were, on the quarry of these
                  murder'd deer,<Br/>To add the death of you.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Merciful heaven!--<Br/>What, man! ne'er pull your hat upon your brows;<Br/>Give sorrow words: the grief that does not
                  speak<Br/>Whispers the o'er-fraught heart, and bids it break.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>My children too?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Wife, children, servants, all<Br/>That could be found.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>And I must be from thence!<Br/>My wife kill'd too?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>I have said.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Be comforted:<Br/>Let's make us medicines of our great revenge,<Br/>To cure this deadly grief.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>He has no children.--All my pretty ones?<Br/>Did you say all?--O hell-kite!--All?<Br/>What, all my pretty chickens and their
                  dam<Br/>At one fell swoop?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Dispute it like a man.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>I shall do so;<Br/>But I must also feel it as a man:<Br/>I cannot but remember such things were,<Br/>That were most precious to
                  me.--Did heaven look on,<Br/>And would not take their part? Sinful Macduff,<Br/>They were all struck for thee! naught that I
                  am,<Br/>Not for their own demerits, but for mine,<Br/>Fell slaughter on their souls: heaven rest them now!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Be this the whetstone of your sword. Let grief<Br/>Convert to anger; blunt not the heart, enrage it.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>O, I could play the woman with mine eye,<Br/>And braggart with my tongue!--But, gentle heavens,<Br/>Cut short all intermission;
                  front to front<Br/>Bring thou this fiend of Scotland and myself;<Br/>Within my sword's length set him; if he 'scape,<Br/>Heaven
                  forgive him too!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>This tune goes manly.<Br/>Come, go we to the king; our power is ready;<Br/>Our lack is nothing but our leave: Macbeth<Br/>Is
                  ripe for shaking, and the powers above<Br/>Put on their instruments. Receive what cheer you may;<Br/>The night is long that never
                  finds the day.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
        </Scenes>
      </Act>
      <Act>
        <Scenes>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Dunsinane. A Room in the Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="DOCTOR GENTLEWOMAN"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>I have two nights watched with you, but can perceive no truth in your report. When was it she last walked?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>Since his majesty went into the field, I have seen her rise from her bed, throw her nightgown upon her, unlock her closet, take
                  forth paper, fold it, write upon it, read it, afterwards seal it, and again return to bed; yet all this while in a most fast
                  sleep.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>A great perturbation in nature,--to receive at once the benefit of sleep, and do the effects of watching-- In this slumbery
                  agitation, besides her walking and other actual performances, what, at any time, have you heard her say?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>That, sir, which I will not report after her.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>You may to me; and 'tis most meet you should.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>Neither to you nor any one; having no witness to confirm my speech. Lo you, here she comes!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="LADYMACBETH">WIth a taper</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>This is her very guise; and, upon my life, fast asleep. Observe her; stand close.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>How came she by that light?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>Why, it stood by her: she has light by her continually; 'tis her command.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>You see, her eyes are open.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>Ay, but their sense is shut.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>What is it she does now? Look how she rubs her hands.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>It is an accustomed action with her, to seem thus washing her hands: I have known her continue in this a quarter of an
                  hour.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Yet here's a spot.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Hark, she speaks: I will set down what comes from her, to satisfy my remembrance the more strongly.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Out, damned spot! out, I say!-- One; two; why, then 'tis time to do't ;--Hell is murky!--Fie, my lord, fie! a soldier, and
                  afeard? What need we fear who knows it, when none can call our power to account?--Yet who would have thought the old man to have had
                  so much blood in him?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Do you mark that?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>The Thane of Fife had a wife; where is she now?--What, will these hands ne'er be clean? No more o' that, my lord, no more o'
                  that: you mar all with this starting.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Go to, go to; you have known what you should not.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>She has spoke what she should not, I am sure of that: heaven knows what she has known.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Here's the smell of the blood still: all the perfumes of Arabia will not sweeten this little hand. Oh, oh, oh!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>What a sigh is there! The heart is sorely charged.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>I would not have such a heart in my bosom for the dignity of the whole body.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Well, well, well,--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>Pray God it be, sir.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>This disease is beyond my practice: yet I have known those which have walked in their sleep who have died holily in their
                  beds.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>Wash your hands, put on your nightgown; look not so pale:--I tell you yet again, Banquo's buried; he cannot come out on's
                  grave.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Even so?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LADYMACBETH">
                <Text>To bed, to bed; there's knocking at the gate: come, come, come, come, give me your hand: what's done cannot be undone: to bed,
                  to bed, to bed.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="LADYMACBETH"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Will she go now to bed?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>Directly.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Foul whisperings are abroad: unnatural deeds<Br/>Do breed unnatural troubles: infected minds<Br/>To their deaf pillows will
                  discharge their secrets.<Br/>More needs she the divine than the physician.--<Br/>God, God, forgive us all!--Look after
                  her;<Br/>Remove from her the means of all annoyance,<Br/>And still keep eyes upon her:--so, good-night:<Br/>My mind she has mated,
                  and amaz'd my sight:<Br/>I think, but dare not speak.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="GENTLEWOMAN">
                <Text>Good-night, good doctor.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The Country near Dunsinane.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MENTEITH CAITHNESS ANGUS LENNOX">With drum and colours. Soldiers.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MENTEITH">
                <Text>The English power is near, led on by Malcolm,<Br/>His uncle Siward, and the good Macduff.<Br/>Revenges burn in them; for their
                  dear causes<Br/>Would to the bleeding and the grim alarm<Br/>Excite the mortified man.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ANGUS">
                <Text>Near Birnam wood<Br/>Shall we well meet them; that way are they coming.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="CAITHNESS">
                <Text>Who knows if Donalbain be with his brother?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>For certain, sir, he is not: I have a file<Br/>Of all the gentry: there is Siward's son<Br/>And many unrough youths, that even
                  now<Br/>Protest their first of manhood.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MENTEITH">
                <Text>What does the tyrant?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="CAITHNESS">
                <Text>Great Dunsinane he strongly fortifies:<Br/>Some say he's mad; others, that lesser hate him,<Br/>Do call it valiant fury: but,
                  for certain,<Br/>He cannot buckle his distemper'd cause<Br/>Within the belt of rule.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ANGUS">
                <Text>Now does he feel<Br/>His secret murders sticking on his hands;<Br/>Now minutely revolts upbraid his faith-breach;<Br/>Those he
                  commands move only in command,<Br/>Nothing in love: now does he feel his title<Br/>Hang loose about him, like a giant's
                  robe<Br/>Upon a dwarfish thief.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MENTEITH">
                <Text>Who, then, shall blame<Br/>His pester'd senses to recoil and start,<Br/>When all that is within him does condemn<Br/>Itself for
                  being there?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="CAITHNESS">
                <Text>Well, march we on,<Br/>To give obedience where 'tis truly ow'd:<Br/>Meet we the medicine of the sickly weal;<Br/>And with him
                  pour we, in our country's purge,<Br/>Each drop of us.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="LENNOX">
                <Text>Or so much as it needs,<Br/>To dew the sovereign flower, and drown the weeds.<Br/>Make we our march towards Birnam.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Dunsinane. A Room in the Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH DOCTOR ATTENDANTS"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Bring me no more reports; let them fly all:<Br/>Till Birnam wood remove to Dunsinane<Br/>I cannot taint with fear. What's the
                  boy Malcolm?<Br/>Was he not born of woman? The spirits that know<Br/>All mortal consequences have pronounc'd me thus,-- "Fear not,
                  Macbeth; no man that's born of woman<Br/>Shall e'er have power upon thee."--Then fly, false thanes,<Br/>And mingle with the English
                  epicures:<Br/>The mind I sway by, and the heart I bear,<Br/>Shall never sag with doubt nor shake with fear.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="SERVANT"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>The devil damn thee black, thou cream-fac'd loon!<Br/>Where gott'st thou that goose look?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SERVANT">
                <Text>There is ten thousand--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Geese, villain?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SERVANT">
                <Text>Soldiers, sir.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Go prick thy face and over-red thy fear,<Br/>Thou lily-liver'd boy. What soldiers, patch?<Br/>Death of thy soul! those linen
                  cheeks of thine<Br/>Are counsellors to fear. What soldiers, whey-face?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SERVANT">
                <Text>The English force, so please you.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Take thy face hence.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="SERVANT"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Seyton!--I am sick at heart,<Br/>When I behold--Seyton, I say!- This push<Br/>Will chair me ever or disseat me now.<Br/>I have
                  liv'd long enough: my way of life<Br/>Is fall'n into the sear, the yellow leaf;<Br/>And that which should accompany old age,<Br/>As
                  honour, love, obedience, troops of friends,<Br/>I must not look to have; but, in their stead,<Br/>Curses, not loud but deep,
                  mouth-honour, breath,<Br/>Which the poor heart would fain deny, and dare not.<Br/>Seyton!--</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="SEYTON"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="SEYTON">
                <Text>What's your gracious pleasure?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>What news more?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SEYTON">
                <Text>All is confirm'd, my lord, which was reported.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I'll fight till from my bones my flesh be hack'd.<Br/>Give me my armour.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SEYTON">
                <Text>'Tis not needed yet.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I'll put it on.<Br/>Send out more horses, skirr the country round;<Br/>Hang those that talk of fear.--Give me mine
                  armour.--<Br/>How does your patient, doctor?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Not so sick, my lord,<Br/>As she is troubled with thick-coming fancies,<Br/>That keep her from her rest.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Cure her of that:<Br/>Canst thou not minister to a mind diseas'd;<Br/>Pluck from the memory a rooted sorrow;<Br/>Raze out the
                  written troubles of the brain;<Br/>And with some sweet oblivious antidote<Br/>Cleanse the stuff'd bosom of that perilous
                  stuff<Br/>Which weighs upon the heart?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Therein the patient<Br/>Must minister to himself.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Throw physic to the dogs,--I'll none of it.--<Br/>Come, put mine armour on; give me my staff:--<Br/>Seyton, send out.--Doctor,
                  the Thanes fly from me.--<Br/>Come, sir, despatch.--If thou couldst, doctor, cast<Br/>The water of my land, find her
                  disease,<Br/>And purge it to a sound and pristine health,<Br/>I would applaud thee to the very echo,<Br/>That should applaud
                  again.--Pull't off, I say.--<Br/>What rhubarb, senna, or what purgative drug,<Br/>Would scour these English hence? Hear'st thou of
                  them?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Ay, my good lord; your royal preparation<Br/>Makes us hear something.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Bring it after me.--<Br/>I will not be afraid of death and bane,<Br/>Till Birnam forest come to Dunsinane.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MACBETH SEYTON"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="DOCTOR">
                <Text>Were I from Dunsinane away and clear,<Br/>Profit again should hardly draw me here.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="DOCTOR"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>

            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Country near Dunsinane: a Wood in view.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MALCOLM SIWARD YOUNGSIWARD MACDUFF MENTEITH CAITHNESS ANGUS LENNOX ROSS SOLDIERS">WIth drum and colours.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Cousins, I hope the days are near at hand<Br/>That chambers will be safe.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MENTEITH">
                <Text>We doubt it nothing.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>What wood is this before us?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MENTEITH">
                <Text>The wood of Birnam.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Let every soldier hew him down a bough,<Br/>And bear't before him; thereby shall we shadow<Br/>The numbers of our host, and make
                  discovery<Br/>Err in report of us.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SOLDIERS">
                <Text>It shall be done.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>We learn no other but the confident tyrant<Br/>Keeps still in Dunsinane, and will endure<Br/>Our setting down before't.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>'Tis his main hope:<Br/>For where there is advantage to be given,<Br/>Both more and less have given him the revolt;<Br/>And none
                  serve with him but constrained things,<Br/>Whose hearts are absent too.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Let our just censures<Br/>Attend the true event, and put we on<Br/>Industrious soldiership.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>The time approaches,<Br/>That will with due decision make us know<Br/>What we shall say we have, and what we owe.<Br/>Thoughts
                  speculative their unsure hopes relate;<Br/>But certain issue strokes must arbitrate:<Br/>Towards which advance the war.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>Dunsinane. Within the castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH SEYTON SOLDIERS">With drum and colours.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Hang out our banners on the outward walls;<Br/>The cry is still, "They come:" our castle's strength<Br/>Will laugh a siege to
                  scorn: here let them lie<Br/>Till famine and the ague eat them up:<Br/>Were they not forc'd with those that should be ours,<Br/>We
                  might have met them dareful, beard to beard,<Br/>And beat them backward home.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>A cry of women within.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="SEYTON">
                <Text>It is the cry of women, my good lord.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="SEYTON"/>
              </Exits>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I have almost forgot the taste of fears:<Br/>The time has been, my senses would have cool'd<Br/>To hear a night-shriek; and my
                  fell of hair<Br/>Would at a dismal treatise rouse and stir<Br/>As life were in't: I have supp'd full with horrors;<Br/>Direness,
                  familiar to my slaught'rous thoughts,<Br/>Cannot once start me.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="SEYTON"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="SEYTON">
                <Text>The queen, my lord, is dead.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>She should have died hereafter;<Br/>There would have been a time for such a word.--<Br/>To-morrow, and to-morrow, and
                  to-morrow,<Br/>Creeps in this petty pace from day to day,<Br/>To the last syllable of recorded time;<Br/>And all our yesterdays have
                  lighted fools<Br/>The way to dusty death. Out, out, brief candle!<Br/>Life's but a walking shadow; a poor player,<Br/>That struts
                  and frets his hour upon the stage,<Br/>And then is heard no more: it is a tale<Br/>Told by an idiot, full of sound and
                  fury,<Br/>Signifying nothing.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MESSENGER"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MESSENGER">
                <Text>Gracious my lord,<Br/>I should report that which I say I saw,<Br/>But know not how to do it.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Well, say, sir.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MESSENGER">
                <Text>As I did stand my watch upon the hill,<Br/>I look'd toward Birnam, and anon, methought,<Br/>The wood began to move.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Liar, and slave!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Strikimg him.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MESSENGER">
                <Text>Let me endure your wrath, if't be not so.<Br/>Within this three mile may you see it coming;<Br/>I say, a moving grove.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>If thou speak'st false,<Br/>Upon the next tree shalt thou hang alive,<Br/>Till famine cling thee: if thy speech be sooth,<Br/>I
                  care not if thou dost for me as much.--<Br/>I pull in resolution; and begin<Br/>To doubt the equivocation of the fiend<Br/>That lies
                  like truth. "Fear not, till Birnam wood<Br/>Do come to Dunsinane;" and now a wood<Br/>Comes toward Dunsinane.--Arm, arm, and
                  out!--<Br/>If this which he avouches does appear,<Br/>There is nor flying hence nor tarrying here.<Br/>I 'gin to be a-weary of the
                  sun,<Br/>And wish the estate o' the world were now undone.--<Br/>Ring the alarum bell!--Blow, wind! come, wrack!<Br/>At least we'll
                  die with harness on our back.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. A Plain before the Castle.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MALCOLM SIWARD MACDUFF SOLDIERS">With drum and colours. Armed with boughs.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Now near enough; your leafy screens throw down,<Br/>And show like those you are.--You, worthy uncle,<Br/>Shall with my cousin,
                  your right-noble son,<Br/>Lead our first battle: worthy Macduff and we<Br/>Shall take upon's what else remains to do,<Br/>According
                  to our order.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>Fare you well.--<Br/>Do we but find the tyrant's power to-night,<Br/>Let us be beaten, if we cannot fight.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Make all our trumpets speak; give them all breath,<Br/>Those clamorous harbingers of blood and death.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. Another part of the Plain.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>They have tied me to a stake; I cannot fly,<Br/>But, bear-like I must fight the course.--What's he<Br/>That was not born of
                  woman? Such a one<Br/>Am I to fear, or none.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="YOUNGSIWARD"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="YOUNGSIWARD">
                <Text>What is thy name?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Thou'lt be afraid to hear it.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="YOUNGSIWARD">
                <Text>No; though thou call'st thyself a hotter name<Br/>Than any is in hell.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>My name's Macbeth.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="YOUNGSIWARD">
                <Text>The devil himself could not pronounce a title<Br/>More hateful to mine ear.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>No, nor more fearful.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="YOUNGSIWARD">
                <Text>Thou liest, abhorred tyrant; with my sword<Br/>I'll prove the lie thou speak'st.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>They fight, and young Seward is slain.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Thou wast born of woman.--<Br/>But swords I smile at, weapons laugh to scorn,<Br/>Brandish'd by man that's of a woman
                  born.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Exits>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACDUFF"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>That way the noise is.--Tyrant, show thy face!<Br/>If thou be'st slain and with no stroke of mine,<Br/>My wife and children's
                  ghosts will haunt me still.<Br/>I cannot strike at wretched kerns, whose arms<Br/>Are hired to bear their staves; either thou,
                  Macbeth,<Br/>Or else my sword, with an unbatter'd edge,<Br/>I sheathe again undeeded. There thou shouldst be;<Br/>By this great
                  clatter, one of greatest note<Br/>Seems bruited. Let me find him, fortune!<Br/>And more I beg not.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="MACDUFF"/>
              </Exits>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MALCOLM SIWARD"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>This way, my lord;--the castle's gently render'd:<Br/>The tyrant's people on both sides do fight;<Br/>The noble thanes do
                  bravely in the war;<Br/>The day almost itself professes yours,<Br/>And little is to do.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>We have met with foes<Br/>That strike beside us.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>Enter, sir, the castle.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all"/>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
          <Scene>
            <Actions>
              <LocationDescription>The same. Another part of the field.</LocationDescription>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACBETH"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Why should I play the Roman fool, and die<Br/>On mine own sword? whiles I see lives, the gashes<Br/>Do better upon them.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MACDUFF"/>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Turn, hell-hound, turn!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Of all men else I have avoided thee:<Br/>But get thee back; my soul is too much charg'd<Br/>With blood of thine already.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>I have no words,--<Br/>My voice is in my sword: thou bloodier villain<Br/>Than terms can give thee out!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>They fight.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Thou losest labour:<Br/>As easy mayst thou the intrenchant air<Br/>With thy keen sword impress, as make me bleed:<Br/>Let fall
                  thy blade on vulnerable crests;<Br/>I bear a charmed life, which must not yield<Br/>To one of woman born.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Despair thy charm;<Br/>And let the angel whom thou still hast serv'd<Br/>Tell thee, Macduff was from his mother's
                  womb<Br/>Untimely ripp'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>Accursed be that tongue that tells me so,<Br/>For it hath cow'd my better part of man!<Br/>And be these juggling fiends no more
                  believ'd,<Br/>That palter with us in a double sense;<Br/>That keep the word of promise to our ear,<Br/>And break it to our
                  hope!--I'll not fight with thee.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Then yield thee, coward,<Br/>And live to be the show and gaze o' the time:<Br/>We'll have thee, as our rarer monsters
                  are,<Br/>Painted upon a pole, and underwrit, "Here may you see the tyrant."</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MACBETH">
                <Text>I will not yield,<Br/>To kiss the ground before young Malcolm's feet,<Br/>And to be baited with the rabble's curse.<Br/>Though
                  Birnam wood be come to Dunsinane,<Br/>And thou oppos'd, being of no woman born,<Br/>Yet I will try the last. Before my body<Br/>I
                  throw my warlike shield: lay on, Macduff;<Br/>And damn'd be him that first cries, "Hold, enough!"</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all">Fighting</Exit>
              </Exits>
              <Entries>
                <Entry role-ref="MALCOLM SIWARD ROSS LENNOX ANGUS CAITHNESS MENTEITH SOLDIERS">With drums and colours.</Entry>
              </Entries>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>I would the friends we miss were safe arriv'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>Some must go off; and yet, by these I see,<Br/>So great a day as this is cheaply bought.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>Macduff is missing, and your noble son.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Your son, my lord, has paid a soldier's debt:<Br/>He only liv'd but till he was a man;<Br/>The which no sooner had his prowess
                  confirm'd<Br/>In the unshrinking station where he fought,<Br/>But like a man he died.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>Then he is dead?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="FLEANCE">
                <Text>Ay, and brought off the field: your cause of sorrow<Br/>Must not be measur'd by his worth, for then<Br/>It hath no end.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>Had he his hurts before?</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="ROSS">
                <Text>Ay, on the front.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>Why then, God's soldier be he!<Br/>Had I as many sons as I have hairs,<Br/>I would not wish them to a fairer death:<Br/>And, so
                  his knell is knoll'd.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>He's worth more sorrow,<Br/>And that I'll spend for him.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="SIWARD">
                <Text>He's worth no more:<Br/>They say he parted well, and paid his score:<Br/>And so, God be with him!--Here comes newer
                  comfort.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Re-enter Macduff, with Macbeth's head.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MACDUFF">
                <Text>Hail, king, for so thou art: behold, where stands<Br/>The usurper's cursed head: the time is free:<Br/>I see thee compass'd with
                  thy kingdom's pearl<Br/>That speak my salutation in their minds;<Br/>Whose voices I desire aloud with mine,--<Br/>Hail, King of
                  Scotland!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Clause role-ref="#all">
                <Text>Hail, King of Scotland!</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Instruction>Flourish.</Instruction>
              <Clause role-ref="MALCOLM">
                <Text>We shall not spend a large expense of time<Br/>Before we reckon with your several loves,<Br/>And make us even with you. My
                  thanes and kinsmen,<Br/>Henceforth be earls, the first that ever Scotland<Br/>In such an honour nam'd. What's more to do,<Br/>Which
                  would be planted newly with the time,--<Br/>As calling home our exil'd friends abroad,<Br/>That fled the snares of watchful
                  tyranny;<Br/>Producing forth the cruel ministers<Br/>Of this dead butcher, and his fiend-like queen,--<Br/>Who, as 'tis thought, by
                  self and violent hands<Br/>Took off her life;--this, and what needful else<Br/>That calls upon us, by the grace of Grace,<Br/>We
                  will perform in measure, time, and place:<Br/>So, thanks to all at once, and to each one,<Br/>Whom we invite to see us crown'd at
                  Scone.</Text>
              </Clause>
              <Exits>
                <Exit role-ref="#all">Flourish.</Exit>
              </Exits>
            </Actions>
          </Scene>
        </Scenes>
      </Act>
    </Acts>
  </Play>
</DramaText>
